<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Faith in Gods promises, the saints best weapon: or, The great use and availableness of faith, both for the support and growth of saints in times most perilous. Plainly discovering that the want of faith in the way of Gods promises, is the great cause of the want of Gods presence. With several considerations for the encrease of faith, tha[t] henceforth the saints may by faith so draw nigh unto God, and in faith so wait upon God, as with certainty of receiving from him. Whereunto is added something concerning the great errour and mistake of many men concerning the true Christ, and how he is said to be in his people; with other things very necessary to be known in order to saints resisting the temptation of the present times. / Set forth as (useful for all people, but) especially intended for the good of such as are returned to the good old way of the Lord, by Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
            <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78621</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R170345</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45578207</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45578207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172158</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78621)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172158)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2616:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Faith in Gods promises, the saints best weapon: or, The great use and availableness of faith, both for the support and growth of saints in times most perilous. Plainly discovering that the want of faith in the way of Gods promises, is the great cause of the want of Gods presence. With several considerations for the encrease of faith, tha[t] henceforth the saints may by faith so draw nigh unto God, and in faith so wait upon God, as with certainty of receiving from him. Whereunto is added something concerning the great errour and mistake of many men concerning the true Christ, and how he is said to be in his people; with other things very necessary to be known in order to saints resisting the temptation of the present times. / Set forth as (useful for all people, but) especially intended for the good of such as are returned to the good old way of the Lord, by Matthew Caffyn ...</title>
                  <author>Caffyn, Matthew, 1628-1714.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by S. Dover, for F. Smith, at the Elephant and Castle, without Temple-Bar.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: p. 11-12 torn with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Friends' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172158:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172158:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>FAITH IN GODS PROMISES, THE Saints beſt Weapon: OR, The great Uſe and Availableneſs of Faith, both for the ſupport and growth of Saints in times moſt perilous. Plainly diſcovering that the want of Faith in the way of Gods Promiſes, is the great cauſe of the want of Gods Preſence. With ſeveral Conſiderations for the encreaſe of Faith, that henceforth the Saints may by Faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo draw nigh unto God, and in Faith ſo wait upon God, as with <hi rend="blackletterType">certainty</hi> of receiving from him. Whereunto is added ſomething concerning the great Errour and Miſtake of many men concerning the True Chriſt, and how he is ſaid to be in his People; with other things very neceſſary to be known in order to Saints reſiſting the Temptation of the preſent Times.</p>
            <p>Set forth as (uſeful for all People, but) eſpecially intended for the good of ſuch as are returned to the Good Old Way of the Lord, By MATTHEW CAFFYN of <hi>Horſham</hi> in <hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>And it is of Faith, that it might be by Grace, <bibl>Rom. 4.16.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>S. Dover,</hi> for <hi>F. Smith,</hi> at the <hi>Eleph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:172158:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172158:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as there are many among the number of Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, that have ſomewhat conſiderably laid out them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Holy purſuit after the more excellent degrees of Chriſtianity, hoth frequently and fervently, ſeeking the Lord in order thereunto, who nevertheleſs yet remain ſhort thereof; and much below the deſired eſtate, to their great diſſatisfaction, even, ſometimes tending to the begetting ſuch temptations as are of a very dangerous conſequence: Theſe things therefore write I unto you, whereby you may (as ſome already have) come to ſee that there is one thing yet much lacking, even Faith, to believe that God is a gracious Rewarder of them that ſeek him; without which, 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God. For though it be true that men have alwayes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, and readily acknowledged, Faith to be that, which great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engages Gods grace and goodneſs for their help; yet Oh! how far have men been from living by Faith indeed, ſo as to eſteem Gods Promiſes their ALL in every condition, and at all times? Whereupon theſe alſo are to direct you unto ſuch enlargedneſſe of heart in believing Gods Promiſes, as may with certainty reach the prayed-for Bleſſings from God; that ſo having ſweet experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Gods Faithfulneſs to your Souls, you may be encouraged
<pb facs="tcp:172158:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> for the future, and made able to ſay (with the Saints of old) I <hi>love the Lord, becauſe he hath heard my Supplications; therefore will I call upon him as long as I live,</hi> Pſal. 116.1,2.</p>
            <p>But as there are ſome who have diligently ſought the Lord, that, for want of believing him to be a faithful Rewarder of ſuch, have notwithſtanding been much without the things ſought for; ſo alſo there are ſome, yea, very many that are apt to ſay (with <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old) <hi>that no evil ſhall come unto them;</hi> and very confident, <hi>that the Lord is among them,</hi> that have indeed no real ground to depend upon the Lord; ſuch and ſo great are their miſcarriages to God-ward, as that their ſeeming Faith and Confidence is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thereby to be meer imaginations, groundleſs perſwaſions, and ſo they found ſuch as <hi>think themſelves to be what they are not, and ſo are deceived:</hi> Theſe are therefore alſo to diſcover and lay open their great miſcarriages and corruptions, even in ſuch perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of theirs, as are ſuppoſed by them to be the beſt of their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, that henceforth they may upon better terms draw nigh unto God, even ſo as that they may enjoy Gods drawing nigh unto them, which is the onely real cauſe of Soul-ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>True it is, that the dayes wherein we live are perilous, and much more may be; yet ſure may you be, that no condition may poſſibly befal you, wherein you may not by Faith ſo lay hold of Gods Promiſes, as nevertheleſs to be greatly ſupported, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly comforted: Wherefore above all things take the ſhield of Faith, and in every condition let the gracious Promiſes of God be the ground of your hopes, and no longer viſible things; that the preſence of the inviſible God may be (with all certainty) experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your Souls: Which, that you may, is, and ſhall be, the Prayers of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Brother in the Lord, MATTHEW CAFFYN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172158:3"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>FAITH IN GODS PROMISES, The Saints beſt Weapon.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the beginning when God made the Heavens and the Earth, it ſeemed good in his ſight, to make and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Mankind to be head over all other his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; to whom he freely gave the glory of Paradiſe (a preſent poſſeſſion of happineſs) which he (during his innocency) enjoyed, not as an inheritance firſt obtained upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional terms, but as a free gift, given him of God, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition required of him in order to his firſt entrance thereinto, <hi>Gen.</hi> 2.8,15,16. Which poſſeſſion when he had loſt by his tra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, and thereby made himſelf and all his poſterity ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt death; ſuch was the Fathers love, as that he freely gave his Son (in due time) to dye for the world, that is, <hi>for every man,</hi> Heb. 2.9. By means whereof was procured a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of all men from the firſt death, with the gift of Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life, and glory, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. Which gift of eternal (and more excellent) life, was as freely given to Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, now ſince his fall, as was that firſt life of happineſs in Paradiſe, before his fall; not upon terms or conditions, nor any fore-ſeen Faith in, or works of Righteouſneſs done by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but meerly, and alone the goodneſs, and richneſs of grace dwelling in God himſelf, moving him thereunto: which life of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry all mankind have right to, and are in ſure capacity thereof, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their infancy (wherefore, <hi>of ſuch,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 19.14. <hi>is the Kingdom of God</hi>) till by their own perſonal tranſgreſſions they procure to themſelves the ſeverity of Gods wrath; that is, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond death, which is Eternal, <hi>John</hi> 3.19. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.14. Under the deſert of which death, all perſons quickly come; all goes out of the way, following the luſts and deſires of the fleſh, which draws, and vehemently inclines to its firſt eſtate of preſent pleaſure, eaſe, and delight, which mankind enjoyed (while he ſtood in his firſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172158:4"/> created eſtate) without thoſe many bodily miſeries which now at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends them, which fleſh and blood would fain be freed from; and ſo it comes to paſs that in all men, in one meaſure or other (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to every mans experience) there ariſeth ſuch natural luſts, and deſires in the fleſh, as greatly provokes them to follow after theſe preſent things, and too too often prevails with them to break the known Laws of God, that ſomething (like to their firſt enjoyments) might be attained: but to follow the preſent glory of this life, ſo as to delight in, and love the ſame (though once lawful for <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, who undoubtedly might then as well love, delight, and take pleaſure therein, as Saints may take pleaſure, and delight in the heavenly glory, when in the real poſſeſſion thereof, though then lawful, yet (I ſay) is not now lawful for the poſterity of <hi>Adam,</hi> becauſe God hath <hi rend="blackletterType">now</hi> commanded (as in very reaſon 'twas meet) that mankind, having loſt (by ſin) the glory of preſent enjoyments (once enjoyable in Paradiſe) and Chriſt having freely purchaſed a more excellent, even, a Heavenly and Eternal glory; (I ſay) God hath <hi rend="blackletterType">now</hi> commanded that mankind ſhould <hi rend="blackletterType">deny themſelves</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">take up a Croſs:</hi> that is to ſay, that men ſhould not <hi rend="blackletterType">now</hi> follow their own natural luſts, which ſo greatly inclines to this preſent world, but ſhould <hi rend="blackletterType">deny and croſs them,</hi> and ſettle their affections and delights upon the more excellent eſtate of glory, purchaſed by the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2. And therefore the ſons of men <hi rend="blackletterType">now</hi> following the natural luſts of the fleſh, become by nature the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath; led by the Prince of the power of the Air, who alſo ſtirs up them to follow their own luſts and hearts deſires, with endeavours (by deceit) to enlarge the ſame; and thus all men go out of the way, <hi>there is none Righteous, no not one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſuch, and ſo great was the Fathers love to the world, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered thus miſerable, lying under the burthen of their own perſonal tranſgreſſions, as that he willed, and accordingly commanded (by the Lord Jeſus) that the Goſpel ſhould be preached to <hi rend="blackletterType">every Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> thereof, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15. that is, The Glad-tydings of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and Remiſſion of their ſins, ſo as that whoſoever of the world (thus miſerable by reaſon of ſin, now repenteth of the ſame) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth and is Baptized, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Ver. 16. But this purpoſe of God concerning Election (that is in Engliſh, chooſing out) all ſuch as believe to life Everlaſting, was not in the leaſt ariſing from, or begotten in God, by, or becauſe of any fore-ſeen Faith in, or works of Righteouſneſs done by the Creature; but meerly, and alone from the purpoſe of his own gracious Will, nothing in man
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172158:4"/> firſt, or laſt, moving him thereunto; for <hi>the purpoſe of God according to Election is</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">not of works, but</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">of him that calleth;</hi> I (with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) bear Witneſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.11.</p>
               <p>And whereas the glory and excellency of Gods preſence, is ſuch, as cannot admit of any unholy or unclean thing; for that <hi rend="blackletterType">Cauſe</hi> his Decree of Election or Predeſtination, reaches the holy Ones, or the number of Believers onely; and not becauſe God ſaw any worth or excellency in mens Faith, or Holineſs, whereby to provoke him thus graciouſly to decree, but according to the <hi rend="blackletterType">good pleaſure of his Will</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>hath he Predeſtinated us,</hi> (that is in Engliſh) <hi>fore-appointed us unto the Adoption of Children,</hi> Epheſ. 1.5.</p>
               <p>Now whoſoever of you (that bear the name of Saints) hearing this ſo gracious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, did in your hearts acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the truth thereof, verily believing, that there was remiſſion of ſins to be had in Chriſt; And that Chriſt therefore (being the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifier, and ſo the moſt amiableſt Object in the World) was moſt worthy your affections, and Soul-deſires, and thereupon reſolved (with godly ſorrow for the ſins paſt) for the time to come to ſerve him with all affections and faithfulneſs, and no longer your ſelves; and ſo committed your ſelves to his grace, confidently depending upon him, for that which you verily believed was to be had in him, even the remiſſion of your ſins, and eternal life; whoſoever of you have <hi rend="blackletterType">So</hi> believed in Chriſt (publickly profeſſing the ſame by being Baptized, that is in Engliſh, Dipped in his Name) by Faith you were juſtified from all your ſins (paſt;) and being thus reconciled, the gift of eternal life, freely purchaſed by Chriſt Jeſus for you, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any reſpect of Faith fore-ſeen in you, or any condition required of you in order thereunto; I ſay, the gift of eternal life remained your portion.</p>
               <p>This Faith being profeſſed by you, next thereunto (O Friends) you may remember, that you with others, and others with you, and for you, made application to the gracious God by Prayer and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, with the Laying on their Hands (according to the Scriptures ſpeaking in that caſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.15,17.) That you might receive the holy Spirit, by the gracious ſupplies of which, you might be both furniſhed to continue the Faith profeſſed, and alſo to bear much fruit therein to the honour of him, who had called you out of darkneſs into his marvellous light.</p>
               <p>But ſince 'tis the receiving of the holy Spirit, and not the bare ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him, nor the much talk of him, that makes men thus happy, and the more and more receiving of him that makes men, men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172158:5"/> even ſtrong in the Faith; it remains a work (none of the leaſt) for all ſuch who have ſo believed, and ſo practiſed, well to conſider what they have received from God, and how they may come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more from him; for it were a lamentable weakneſs (even greatly tending to the provoking of God) for men practiſing as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, to reſt, and lye ſtill ſecure, as if all were well, barely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they have called upon the Lord for his holy Spirit, when (for a long time) they know him not received; nothing of this work upon their own heatts, whereby they can declare to others, what the Lord hath done for <hi rend="blackletterType">their Souls. David</hi> (that heavenly pattern) being in the profeſſion of the Law of God, reſted not in that, but <hi>followed</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">hard after the Lord therein,</hi> Pſal. 63.8. to whom having diligently ſought, and Prayed often, he abode waiting upon him, till the Lord gave him ground to ſay to his Soul; <hi>Return unto</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">hath dealt bountifully with thee,</hi> Pſal. 116.7. and as elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.8. <hi rend="blackletterType">Thy right hand upholdeth me.</hi> How good a thing were it for Profeſſors in this day, to take pattern here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſo as henceforth not to content themſelves, in that formerly they have prayed (with ſubjection to the Laying on of Hands) for the gift of Gods Spirit; nor in that they continue (ſometimes) yet to pray for the ſame, for moſt ſurely 'tis the <hi rend="blackletterType">known hand of God</hi> upon the Soul, that onely can give real cauſe of ſatisfaction, the certain experience of Gods bountifulneſs renders poor Souls (otherwiſe reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs) to be at reſt and true peace: And then how boldly may ſuch ſpeak of Gods goodneſs to others, having themſelves ſweet experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his goodneſs to their <hi rend="blackletterType">own Souls?</hi> And how boldly may ſuch ſtand up and exhort others to keep under, and mortifie the deeds of the body; they in the mean while knowing the deeds of the Body mortified <hi rend="blackletterType">in themſelves,</hi> through the operation of Gods Spirit upon their Souls? Yea, and how boldly alſo may ſuch reprove them, that ſhall notwithſtanding live after the fleſh? whereas otherwiſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof of the reprover, reflects and ſticks faſt on himſelf; and not onely ſo, but there is this miſchief alſo attending, even that thereby the fleſhly part in the reproved, hath occaſion given it to follow its luſts; and ſo how great are the retortings and reflections of ſuch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the reprover?</p>
               <p>Sure I am that for men to have, long after the practice of Gods Ordinances, no other plea nor ground, to contend for the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Adverſaries, but barely becauſe ſuch Ordinances are ſpoken of in the Scriptures, is that which verily tends to diſcouragement, and Soul-faintings therein; yea at length to ſay, (with thoſe careleſs ones
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172158:5"/> of old) What profit is it that we have kept his Ordinances? <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.14. When as men hearing the Goſpel of Chriſt, which promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth reſt and peace to the Soul, through the Remiſſion of ſins, with the gift of Gods Spirit; have thereupon ſubjected to the Goſpel with ſuch a renewed mind, as would not be ſatisfied with hearing of the good things thereof, till they were able to ſay, that as they had heard, <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo they have ſeen;</hi> that which was promiſed, <hi rend="blackletterType">our Souls have taſted;</hi> reſt and peace we know, the fruits of Gods Spirit we experience, &amp;c. Whenas (I ſay) men, thus following hard after the Lord, have this knowledge of Gods goodneſs and powerful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in his Way, as a great Argument, together with Scripture Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, to embolden them to contend for the Way, and to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them againſt all oppoſitions.</p>
               <p>'Tis common amongſt men to look upon themſelves, diſcharged from duty of love to ſuch Beggars, who after their asking for Almes, ſhall preſently turn their backs, and mind other matters of trifle, more than their reaſonable waiting to receive what they have asked for. Now may any ſo much as once think, that God will turn his face (in love) to ſuch, who ſometimes ſhall ask of him Spiritual Almes, but preſently are found (as it were) turning their backs to the Throne of Grace, and not waiting there; as if their receiving of Grace were little minded by them (which is <hi rend="blackletterType">onely</hi> the Chriſtian mans life) but rather other things more, meer trifles, compared to what they have asked for of God; their hearts (may be) running af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter covetouſneſs, as the hearts of Iſrael were, who nevertheleſſe would be ſpreading forth their hands before God, <hi>but they flattered him with their lips, and lied before him with their tongues, and he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded them not,</hi> Pſal. 78.36. May any (I ſay) once think that God will turn his face (in love) to, and not rather withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi rend="blackletterType">far</hi> from ſuch, as perſons greatly unworthy of his benevolence to whom he is no wayes engaged by promiſe to do any thing for them, ſince they come not up to the terms of his goodneſs? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, delay to conſider theſe things is very dangerous, even nigh to, an irrecoverable eſtate.</p>
               <p>There hath been indeed much contending for this Principle of Laying on of Hands, and great pains taken both by ſpeaking and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the ſame; and <hi>I bear them record, that they therein have had zeal for the Truth</hi> (for ſo I do, and hope ever ſhall, believe it to be) <hi>but</hi> (alas!) <hi>their zeal hath not been according to true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> if they have not as well, yea, and much more too, in the mean time, endeavoured that the great end of this Ordinance might be
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172158:6"/> obtained, to wit, the ſanctification, ſtrengthning &amp; guidance of their Souls in the Truth of God; without which both their ſubjection to the Doctrine thereof, and alſo their much pleadings for the ſame, would be of no effect.</p>
               <p>But I hope better things (at leaſtwiſe of many) though I thus ſpeak, being perſwaded that there are ſuch who (knowing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a juſtified Eſtate through faith in Chriſt) have a clear ſight and <hi rend="blackletterType">deep ſence</hi> of their ſouls wants, as not knowing how to live, nor to work in Gods ſervices, without the gracious ſupplies of Gods Spirit: (which ſight and deep ſence of want is ſeen through their great (Heaven-born) deſires to honour God, which deſires ſprings from their Souls great love to God, which love in them to God-ward, is begotten by Gods great love <hi rend="blackletterType">firſt to them,</hi> 1 John 4.19.</p>
               <p>And that theſe hereupon have a very high eſteem of Gods ſpiritual preſence (being the true Bread from above, which onely will ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Souls born from above) valuing it far above the preſence of all things whatſoever, ſeeing more worth and excellency therein, than in any thing of the world. True it is, that moſt Profeſſors confeſſe and talk of ſuch things, but theſe experienceth the ſame in <hi rend="blackletterType">their Souls,</hi> and ſo their Righteouſneſs exceedeth the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe many lifeleſs and ſenſeleſs Profeſſors, who as much as others talks of theſe things, but knows it not in themſelves.</p>
               <p>And that theſe hereupon do greatly deſire the preſence of Gods Spirit; and ſo both frequently and fervently are found praying for the ſame, <hi>lifting up holy hands to the Lord,</hi> and (being in <hi>Davids</hi> ſence) with all earneſtneſs (<hi>David</hi>-like) beſeech the Lord <hi>to make haſt for their help, and to make</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">no tarrying,</hi> Pſal. 40.17.</p>
               <p>And that theſe, till the Lord doth viſit them with the ſpecial Graces of his Holy Spirit, are found mourning before the Lord, and greatly complaining againſt themſelves, as being wonderfully ſhort and low in their own apprehenſions, as to what God requires, and which they know is due to his Name: Wherefore their ſouls (like <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 77.2.) <hi rend="blackletterType">refuſeth to be comforted</hi> with any thing, though the very chiefeſt of this worlds enjoyments; they looking upon themſelves as ſuch who want all things, while the ſupplies of Grace is wanting.</p>
               <p>And that theſe, during the time that the Lord withholds the viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his Grace, are not onely continuing in Prayer, but <hi rend="blackletterType">walking</hi> therein, <hi>communing with their own hearts, and</hi> (like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in ſuch a caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.) <hi>making diligent ſearch,</hi> fearing leaſt there ſhould be ſome ſecret ſin, for which cauſe the Lord may for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear to draw nigh to their Souls.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:172158:6"/>
               <p>And that theſe (while in this capacity) think it not much, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delight to ſpend dayes in the Cloſet, there to humble themſelves with <hi rend="blackletterType">Faſting</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">Prayer</hi> before the Lord, not as Phariſees do, to be ſeen of men, neither as ſluggards do, becauſe they read that Saints formerly did, and now ſometimes doth ſo; but purely and zealouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are led out thereunto, from that <hi rend="blackletterType">vehemency of deſires and Soul-affections</hi> which they experience in themſelves, after the more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent eſtate; for as God hath graciouſly opened their underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to know that there is an excellent eſtate attainable; their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction is not in the knowledge thereof, nor in the much talk thereabouts, nor in the ready Confeſſion, that the ſame is excellent, and of a ſpecial goodneſs (as is too much the ſatisfaction of ſome) but rather in <hi rend="blackletterType">living the life thereof,</hi> even, that <hi rend="blackletterType">their Souls</hi> may be ſpiritually framed, nnd wonderfully ſtrengthened with might, both to the pure doing what is ſpiritually good, and alſo to the <hi>renouncing of the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">hidden things of diſhoneſty,</hi> 2 Cor. 4.2.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as there are ſuch that are found (to ſome conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable degree) thus prizing, and ſo following hard after ſpiritual Bleſſings, that thereby they (having ſo far taſted of the Lords good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as to know themſelves in a juſtified eſtate from ſin by his Grace) might now for the time to come bear much fruit to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Name; who notwithſtanding yet come ſhort, and are much below that more excellent eſtate, which they have longed for, and which is certainly to be attained: Theſe are therefore to inform (or remind) all ſuch, that there is yet one thing much lacking, namely, <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith,</hi> or the ſtedfaſt believing Gods Promiſes, graciouſly made in order thereunto; for they that come to God, <hi>muſt believe, not onely that God is, or that he is diligently to be ſought unto; but alſo that he is a Rewarder of ſuch as thus ſeek him,</hi> (mark) <hi>you</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">muſt believe</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.) ſhewing plainly, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what meaſure ſoever of holineſſe in point of converſation, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency of ſeeking, or importunity of praying there is, unleſſe it be accompanied with faith in the Soul, that God will reward, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as he hath Promiſed, all other virtues found in the Creature will not reach the deſired Bleſſings from God; For without <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which alſo agrees the Adviſe of the Apoſtle, ſaying, let us <hi>draw near with a true heart,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in full aſſurance of Faith, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 10.22 Moreover, <hi>I will,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that men pray every where, lifting up holy hands, without wrath and</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">doubting,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.8. Shewing that it is not enough for men to lift up holy hands to God, though
<pb facs="tcp:172158:7"/> attended alſo with Charity, ſo as to be without wrath (both which are very ſpecial things) unleſſe attended alſo with that (more ſpecial) vertue of Faith, ſo as to be <hi rend="blackletterType">without doubting;</hi> not enough (I ſay) whereby to reach the prayed-for Bleſſings from God: for as 'tis the duty of Saints alwayes to be ready to do Gods Commandements, thereby to acknowledge and declare him to be the Supream, and Almighty God; ſo alſo 'tis their duty al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be ready to believe Gods Promiſes, thereby to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and declare him to be a juſt and faithful God; <hi>for they that receive his Teſtimony, ſets to their ſeals that God</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">is true,</hi> John 3.33. Both which being experienced by the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> cauſed him boldly to pray, and confidently to conclude, that he ſhould not ſlide, ſaying, <hi>Judge me, O Lord, for I have walked in mine</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">integrity, I have</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">alſo truſted in the Lord;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">therefore I ſhall not ſlide,</hi> Pſal. 26.1. Both which alſo being found in the Prophet <hi>Daniel,</hi> did (as it were) fetch from God an extraordinary power for the ſtopping the Lyons mouths, ſo as that he had not (though among them) the leaſt hurt? And why? <hi>Becauſe of his</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">innocency towards God and man,</hi> Dan. 6.22. and <hi rend="blackletterType">becauſe he believed in his God,</hi> ver. 23.</p>
               <p>True it is, that God hath promiſed his Spirit to them that ask him; but 'tis worthy all obſervation (and I pray you to mark) what kind of asking it is, which the Promiſe is made to; which you may obſerve from Chriſts own words, where he ſaith, <hi>What things ſoever ye deſire, when ye pray,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">believe that ye receive them,</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">ye ſhall have them,</hi> Mark 11.24. To which agrees <hi>Pauls</hi> Teſtimony, to wit, <hi>That we might receive the promiſe of the Holy Spirit,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">through Faith,</hi> Gal. 3.14. Plainly diſcovering what kind of Prayer it is, Gods ears are open unto, which I wiſh all your hearts may be open to conſider, even that it is the <hi rend="blackletterType">Prayer of Faith,</hi> that reaches the Bleſſing from God, whereby to ſtrengthen the weak and ſickly Soul: for when Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſhall be ſo magnified in the heart, as that (like <hi>Abraham</hi>) there ſhall not be ſo much as a conſidering the deadneſs of its own body, (that is to ſay, its own weakneſs and inability to bring forth fruit to God) but ſhall confidently relye upon his Promiſes, conſidering that he is both able and willing to cauſe the barren womb to bear (even, the unlikelieſt of men, the baſe things of the world, things that are not, to confound the things that are, even, the Wiſe and Prudent of the World) ſurely, Gods ears are open to hear the Prayers of ſuch, they ſhall not go empty away; but rather (as 'tis written) <hi>ſhall be like the Tree planted by the waters, that ſhall not ſee when heat cometh, whoſe leaf ſhall be green, and ſhall not be careful in the year</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:172158:7"/> 
                  <hi>of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yielding fruit,</hi> Jer. 17.7,.8</p>
               <p>When <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old diſtruſted the help of the Lord, and ſo went <hi>down into Egypt for help,</hi> the Lord ſpake unto them, ſaying, <hi rend="blackletterType">In quietneſs and confidence ſhall be your ſtrength,</hi> Iſa. 30.2,3,15. Shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if <hi>Iſrael</hi> had been quiet, ſo as not to have ſtirred for <hi>Egypts</hi> help, but in confidence (or Faith) ſtayed upon the Lord, he (even the Lord) would have been their ſtrength and Salvation, ſo as that they needed not to have feared, <hi>though an Hoſt had riſen up againſt them;</hi> but (alas!) <hi rend="blackletterType">becauſe of their unbelief, God could do no mighty work of deliverance for them;</hi> for, ſaid they, <hi>We will flee upon Horſes, and ride upon the ſwift;</hi> and therefore God (in his wrath and great diſpleaſure againſt them) ſaid, <hi>That thoſe that ſhould purſue them ſhould be ſwift, a thouſand (of them) ſhould flye at the rebuke of</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">one, and the ſhadow of Egypt ſhould be their ſhame,</hi> ver. 3, 16, 17. <hi>and he would wait that he might be gracious,</hi> ver. 18. If peradventure, when they had taſted of his Judgements, they would thenceforth believe in him, and confidently relye upon him, that ſo he might be their ſtrength.</p>
               <p>So much to do hath Faith with the powerful Vertue of the Lord, (it being the Lords pleaſure that it ſhould) as that when the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that had an iſſue of blood twelve years, was cured by means of the Vertue that was in Chriſt, he caſts her Cure upon her Faith, ſaying, <hi>Daughter</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">thy Faith hath made the whole,</hi> Mark 5.34. So likewiſe the Sanctification or Cleanſing of the heart, is aſcribed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith,</hi> Acts 26.18. Yet not in the leaſt, as if Faith <hi rend="blackletterType">of it ſelf,</hi> or in its <hi rend="blackletterType">own ſtrength,</hi> could ſanctifie or cleanſe any heart (or cure any mans body) for that is the proper work of that ſpiritual Vertue and Power which is in the Lord: but inaſmuch as the good pleaſure of his good Will is, that the ſame powerful vertue ſhall ſerve for the cure of none, but ſuch as ſhall touch him <hi rend="blackletterType">by Faith,</hi> whereby to draw the Soul-healing Vertue from him; therefore 'tis ſaid, that <hi>through Faith men are ſanctified; and kept by the Power of God through Faith to Salvation.</hi> So tha notwithſtanding the readineſs, and great willingneſs that there is in God, to cure the diſtempered and diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Souls (as his many Promiſes and gracious Proteſtations in order thereunto plainly declares) yet unleſs they ſhall make ſelious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>arty Applications unto him, together with a holy dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, and a ſerious waiting in Faith for the ſame; they may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs remain very much out of frame, and greatly unhealthful in their Souls; there being not ground otherwiſe for the Lord (the great Curer of Souls) to ſay, <hi>Sons and Daughters,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">your Faith hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ade you whole.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172158:8"/>
               <p>When the Church of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> were likely to faint in their Minds, the Apoſtle (being greatly deſirous of their holding out) could find no better way (it appears) then mightily to preſſe them to a cloſe dependance upon God by Faith; and therefore he begins his account from <hi>Abel,</hi> who <hi>through faith obtained witneſſe that he was Righteous, and being dead, yet ſpeaketh;</hi> and ſo down to <hi>Enoch, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and the reſt of the Fathers and Prophets, who through Faith obtained a good report, wrought Righteouſneſs, obtained Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; mentioning many other alſo, as well extraordinary as ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary deliverances obtained by Faith, and yet he mentions not all he could touching the Power of Faith; for himſelf ſaith, <hi>That the time would fail him to tell thereof,</hi> Heb. 11. Now what leſs is there to be learned, by this ſo large an account of the Apoſtle touching Faith, then that Faith is ſomewhat more concerned in the receiving ſpiritual Power and Divine Light from God, in order to their ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and thriving in his way, than any other thing (on the Creatures part) whatſoever? As elſewhere, the Apoſtle mentioning divers pieces of Armour, wherewith Chriſtians are to be attired (not one of which but that is of ſpecial concernment) yet (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16.) <hi rend="blackletterType">Above all things take the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ld of Faith, wherewith you ſhall be able</hi> (through the Grace handed to the Soul by Faith) <hi>to quench</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">all the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">fiery Darts of the wicked; for none of them that tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in the Lord ſhall be left deſolate,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.22. So much doth Faith carry the ſence and ſcope of the Goſpel-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, as that ſometimes the Apoſtles called it, <hi rend="blackletterType">the Faith,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Jude</hi> 3. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.23. <hi>And it is of Faith</hi> (mark it I pray) <hi>that it might be</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">by Grace,</hi> Rom. 4.16.</p>
               <p>Now then if it be ſo, that mens prayers to God, though never ſo many or largely performed, renders them not happy; but that their happineſſe conſiſts in their receivings from God what they have prayed for; and that the way (propoſed by God) wherein perſons may come to receive from him, is not onely for them <hi>to lift up Holy hands to God,</hi> but that alſo they be <hi rend="blackletterType">without doubting;</hi> that is to ſay, ſuch as believe that they ſhall receive what they have ſought for; it remains a weighry work for every Goſpel-profeſſing Soul, well to conſider of what nature and kind their applications have been, which they have made to God; conſidering that his grace and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is no otherwiſe engaged for their Souls help, but as they ſhall rely and depend on him, to receive the ſame by Faith: which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, and believed as true, may well remove all doubts and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicions concerning the way of God, which ſometimes ariſe in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172158:8"/> Profeſſors thereof, upon the account of ſo little received from God; for undoubtedly the Lords hand is not ſhortned, his way he hath not left, his Promiſes thereunto are Yea, and Amen, in the Lord; but alas! How ſhort have men been in coming up to the terms of his goodneſs? That part of Gods Word which conſiſts of Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, men indeed have been ſomewhat buſied about; but as for that part which conſiſteth of Promiſes, Oh how little hath it been minded! they have been indeed often read of, and ſometimes tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of; But how are they that have ſeriouſly pondred them, and in their hearts magnified them, ſo as to wait in, and live upon them, counting them <hi rend="blackletterType">all things</hi> to them, in every condition?</p>
               <p>Haſt thou then (O thou that out-ſtrippeſt ſome others in thy zeal after ſpiritual things) haſt thou (I ſay) often viſited the Throne of Grace (as a work moſt pleaſant to thy Soul) beſeeching the Lord to draw nigh to thee, in the large givings forth of his Grace to thy Soul (well knowing that without it all thy drawings nigh to him is nothing) and haſt thou there waited in the ſight of the worth and excellency thereof, and ſo in the ſence of thy great need of the ſame; <hi>thy Soul</hi> (as it were <hi>fainting, and thine eyes</hi> (like the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets) <hi>failing for the Word of God;</hi> that is, the Word of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to be fulfilled to thy Soul, ſaying (with him in thy Soul-long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings after the deſired Bread from above, to refreſh and ſtrengthen thy Soul, born anew from above) <hi>when, Lord, wilt thou comfort me?</hi> Pſal. 119.81,82. (I ſay) haſt thou thus waited upon God, and art thou yet often with God in thy moſt ſolemn and ſerious Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? O do but now give the Lord, (<hi>who waiteth to be gracious,</hi> being as willing to do good, as thou art deſirous of good) give the Lord (I ſay) ground to ſay to thee (as once the Woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Matth. 15.28.) O man, <hi rend="blackletterType">great is thy Faith;</hi> and then, O then will the Lord readily ſay to thee, <hi rend="blackletterType">Be it unto thee, even as thou wilt: according to thy faith be it unto thee.</hi> But if otherwiſe, the account will be a ſad and doleful account, even, that the Lord <hi rend="blackletterType">could do</hi> no mighty work of love for thee, <hi rend="blackletterType">becauſe of thy unbelief,</hi> Matth. 13.58. Mark 6.5,6. O that all were wiſe (that bear the name of Saints) even with the Wiſdom which is from above: So that the bare knowledge of theſe things, or the much talk (or preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) of them to others, might not be their ſatisfaction, but that all would rather carefully and ſpeedily endeavour to know, and be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, that they themſelves <hi rend="blackletterType">doth ſo</hi> wait upon God by Faith, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently <hi rend="blackletterType">doth ſo</hi> receive from him, which to know, and experience within, is real cauſe and ground of peace, and Soul-ſatisfaction.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172158:9"/>
               <p>In order whereunto, even, that Faith may grow and flouriſh in your Souls, conſider (O Friends) whether we are not to believe that a Son ſhall be given, when God hath promiſed it, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the leaſt heed, to what the deadneſs of body on either hand may ſay? <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.19,20.</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe that the promiſed Seed ſhall be <hi>as the Stars for multitude,</hi> when God hath ſpoken it? <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.5,6. notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the fleſhly oppoſition ariſing from the Commandement to ſlay <hi>Iſaac,</hi> the onely promiſed Seed, from whence the multitude ſhould come forth.</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe that the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God ſhall be brought into the good Land, flowing with Milk and Honey, when God (that cannot lye) hath ſpoken it, notwithſtanding all the gain-ſayings of the red Sea before, and the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Hoſt behind?</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe and confidently to expect a great plenty, even, <hi>a meaſure of fine Flower for a ſhekel, and two meaſures of Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a ſhekel, and that ſo ſoon as to morrow,</hi> when the Lord God hath ſpoken it, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 7.1. notwithſtanding the many and great oppoſitions and contrary ſpeakings of this dayes poverty, even, <hi>that an Aſſes head is ſold for fourſcore pieces of Silver, and the fourth part of a Cab of Doves dung for five pieces of Silver?</hi> Chap. 6.25. And was not unbelief in this Promiſe the cauſe of ſudden Judgement ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king hold upon the mighty man, upon whom the King leaned? <hi>Chap.</hi> 7.2,19,20.</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe that the mighty Hoſts of the <hi>Midianites,</hi> and <hi>Amalekites,</hi> who for multitude <hi>are as Graſhoppers, and their Camels as the ſand by the Sea-ſhore,</hi> ſhall be put to flight, when the Lord of Hoſts hath ſpoken it, notwithſtanding all the ſtrong reaſonings of fleſh and blood (that is for walking by ſight) becauſe there is no more than three hundred men allowed by God to do it? <hi>Judg.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe that the Meal in the Barrel, and the Oyl in the Cruſe ſhall not waſte nor fail, when the faithful God hath ſpoken it, though never ſo much contradicted by the nature of fleſh and blood, becauſe that at preſent it is but a <hi rend="blackletterType">handful</hi> of Meal in a Barrel, and but a <hi rend="blackletterType">little</hi> Oyl in a Cruſe? 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17.</p>
               <p>Are we not to believe that the great Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> ſhall fall down flat, there being a Promiſe of God that they ſhall, without giving any heed to the many fleſhly gain-ſayings, becauſe of their height, or great ſtrength, or becauſe of the low means (<hi>as blowing in Rams-horns</hi>) appointed of God in order thereunto? Joſh. 6.</p>
               <p>The ſum of all which is, whether ſuch as have attained to a ſtate
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172158:9"/> of Juſtification from their old ſins by Faith in Chriſt, are not in Faith and full aſſurance to wait for the gift of the Holy Spirit, whereby to carry on, and work through the work begun (which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will never be finiſhed) there being a plain and moſt certain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God <hi>to pour out the ſame,</hi> John 2.28,29. Act. 2.38. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt hearkning to fleſhly gain-ſayings, or yielding to fleſhly dulneſs or any miſtruſt, becauſe of the low means (as Impoſition of Hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1.2. <hi>Act.</hi> 8.12,15,17.) appointed of God in order thereunto, or whatſoever elſe ſhall attempt the making his word of Promiſe of no effect? Yea, and not onely a Promiſe of God, but alſo very ſtrong provocations whereby to believe the ſame, being aſſured from the Lord Jeſus, that he doth not onely <hi rend="blackletterType">as readily</hi> as Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers that are evil, give to their Children, but <hi rend="blackletterType">how much more will your heavenly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him,</hi> Luke 11.13.</p>
               <p>That is, the Scriptures compared, the Lords good pleaſure and great freeneſs is to give his Holy Spirit to them that ask him, <hi>with lifting up of Holy hands unto him,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in Faith,</hi> that they ſhall receive from him, <hi>Mal.</hi> 21.22. And ſo waiting with opportunity, till they do receive him, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.8,9. ſo as to know his Power, and enjoy his Comfort and Light in their Souls: that as <hi>uncleanneſs, wrath, ſtrife,</hi> with many other ſuch manifeſt fruits of the fleſh, heretofore reigned in them; now <hi>love, joy, peace, gentleneſs, goodneſs,</hi> with many other ſuch like Vertues, the manifeſt fruits of the Spirit, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. for where ſuch things are deſigned by the Soul, ſo as that all other enjoyments of the world gives no ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to it, while this ſpiritual frame is wanting, which it deſires of any thing, yea, above all things that the world can afford, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon have diligently ſought the Lord for it, and now ſetting to its ſeal that God is True, by believing that he is a Rewarder of them that ſo ſeek him: where (I ſay) ſpiritual things are thus deſigned, Gods ears are open to hear their Prayers, he will be nigh unto them in all conditions.</p>
               <p>Moreover, for the growing and flouriſhing of Faith, conſider that the Lord ſought after you, when you ſought not after him, and ſaid to you when you were in your blood, <hi rend="blackletterType">turn, turn, for why will ye dye? Turn at my reproof, and I will pour out my Spirit unto you,</hi> Pro. 1.23. And all this before you ſaw any beauty or excellency in the Holy Spirit, and ſo had no deſire after him, and therefore ſought not God for him; and yet even then God thus magnified the riches of his Grace in the kind tenders thereof to you, <hi rend="blackletterType">while ſuch;</hi> And will
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172158:10"/> he not now <hi rend="blackletterType">much more</hi> take care for you, and poſſeſs you with that, which he before tendered unto you, even, the comfortable preſence of his Holy Spirit? Since you are now turned unto him, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his ſervants, not ſeeking the honour of the world as before, but his Holy Spirit, whereby to do him ſervice for the honour of his Name; Will he not much more (I ſay) tender ſuch? Will he with-hold his good Spirit from ſuch, He, the Lord the Righteous God, that hath ſaid, <hi>He will with-hold</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">no good thing from ſuch as walk uprightly?</hi> Pſal. 84.11. <hi rend="blackletterType">Surely no;</hi> Hath God begot by his Word of Truth, brought to the birth, cauſed the Man-child (the New-creature) to be born into the world, to whom he ſaith, <hi rend="blackletterType">Open thy mouth wide, and I will</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">fill it,</hi> Pſal. 81.10. and may you judge, and not deſperately ſin through unbelief, that God will now ſtarve this New-creature of his own begetting, and bringing forth, that he will with-hold the ſpiritual Bread, which onely will ſatisfie it, and ſo famiſh his own adopted Children, as ſtarve they muſt, and ſtarve they will, if God give not his Holy Spirit unto them? No, <hi rend="blackletterType">ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no;</hi> carnal men will not ſtarve, but nouriſh and cheriſh their Children; And will not God, who is rich in mercy, and deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in mercy, nouriſh his? Yea, <hi>how</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">much more will your Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father give the Holy Spirit to them that ask him</hi> (as aboveſaid.) Moreover, conſider that God having promiſed his Holy Spirit to ſuch as ſeek him with Faith to receive the ſame, both his <hi rend="blackletterType">Faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Righteouſneſs is engaged</hi> for them that ſo ſeek him, which the holy and believing man fears not to make mention before the Lord, ſaying (with <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Hear me O Lord in thy Faithfulneſs, and in thy Righteouſneſs,</hi> Pſal. 143.1.</p>
               <p>Moreover, for men highly to eſteem Gods Promiſes, and ſo to mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie them in their hearts, as that all pleading of Fleſh, World, or Devil, becauſe of, the deadneſs of body, or barrenneſs of the womb, ſhall be utterly rejected, as not worthy to be conſidered, when God hath ſpoken: (I ſay) for men thus to eſteem Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes (there being every whit as much reaſon for them ſo to do, as to eſteem and keep his Commandments) is not onely the way leading to their Happineſs, but alſo that which mightily <hi rend="blackletterType">gives glory</hi> to God. <hi>Abraham ſtaggered not at the Promiſe of God through unbelief, but was ſtrong in Faith,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">giving glory to God,</hi> Rom. 4.20.</p>
               <p>Theſe things write I unto you (O Friends) that henceforth your ſences might be much exerciſed, and your minds more and more bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in the conſideration of theſe (and ſuch like) things, that the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which you have of Gods Promiſes, may be a word ſo <hi rend="blackletterType">planted</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:172158:10"/> in your underſtandings by Faith, as that all fleſhly ſtaggerings and carnal oppoſitions may fall down before it, and by ſuch endeavours on your part, you ſhal appear to be ſuch who are obedient to the whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Counſel of the Apoſtle, who exhorted <hi>Timothy to follow after Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, Charity,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith, Meekneſs, Patience,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.11. Who queſtionleſs knew how Faith was to be obtained, as well as any of thoſe that ſpeak ſo much of Faith's being the gift of God; who being almoſt, if not altogether, ſilent concerning mens following after Faith, have thereby (I greatly fear) been a means to freeze up the deſires of men, and wholly to ſtop their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, after Faith, which (if ſo) I could wiſh that henceforth they would hearken unto the Apoſtle, who puts men upon <hi rend="blackletterType">following after Faith,</hi> equally (obſerve it) as he puts them to follow after Meekneſs, or Patience, &amp;c. Which conſidered, may be a means to thaw them out of that benummed and frozen eſtate, even unto due conſiderations and ſerious ſtirrings on their parts, in order unto the growth and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Faith.</p>
               <p>And withal be ſure that your Prayers and Supplications be not wanting to the Lord, that he would be pleaſed <hi>to encreaſe your Faith,</hi> and ſo ſhall you in due time come to experience the being of Faith in you, after ſpecial degrees, wrought there by the operation of Gods Spirit, according to <hi>Pauls</hi> words to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Chap. 6.22. while you diligently ſought, and carefully <hi>followed after Faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his words to Timothy,</hi> Chap. 6.11.</p>
               <p>Together with theſe things, let it not be thought a needleſs work, or beſides the buſineſs in hand, to conſider whether Saints are not now (in theſe latter dayes wherein 'tis evil, as appears by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, to depart from the Faith profeſſed in former Apoſtolical dayes, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.) whether Saints (I ſay) are not now to ſeek for, and in Faith to wait whereby to receive the Spirit, with the ſame parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular gifts and operations which Saints formerly enjoyed, in order to their carrying on the great Work of the Goſpel, both among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others? Since God in his making Promiſe of <hi>pouring out the Spirit upon his People,</hi> (which Promiſe we in theſe latter dayes flye unto as the ground of our Faith) makes mention alſo of ſeveral gifts of the ſame Spirit, <hi>John</hi> 2.28,29. And withal conſidering, that the Apoſtles exhorted the Churches <hi>earneſtly to covet, and follow after the ſeveral gifts of the Spirit,</hi> 1 Cor. 12.28,29,30,31. 14.1,39. Which exhortations, if they reach us, and ſpeak to us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> much as any other Scripture-exhortations (which for any to deny is hard) then, Oh then! great need have all to pray, <hi rend="blackletterType">Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:172158:11"/>
               <p>But in reference to the fore-mentioned drawing nigh unto God by Faith, I ſuppoſe that which is a very general hinderance thereof, is the great unworthineſs that perſons find in themſelves by reaſon of ſin, by means whereof they are (as it were) afraid to draw near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; or however if they do, 'tis very coldly, having little or no hopes of acceptance with the Lord; and ſo being not in a juſtified eſtate from ſin, are without Faith in reference to the ſpecial Graces of Gods Spirit: but among theſe there are ſome, much more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy than others, who by reaſon of the ſtrength and ſubtilty of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, ſometimes (as well as others) tranſgreſs the Laws of God, but not as ſuch who <hi rend="blackletterType">overtake ſin,</hi> but rather are <hi>overtaken</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">with ſin,</hi> Gal. 6.1. Not allowing themſelves therein, as their great trouble, and Soul-heavineſs, with daily complaints becauſe thereof, plainly declares; and yet theſe for want of a right underſtanding Gods Way to juſtifie ſinners, and his readineſs to juſtifie them; alas! even theſe go mourning all the day long, rather decaying than flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing in the Way of God. You, even you in particular (the beloved of my Soul) do I hereby exhort:</p>
               <p>Firſt, That ye alwayes abide watchful, and abundantly careful <hi>that ye ſin not: But,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>If any man ſin, that you remember there is an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, who is a propitiation for our ſins,</hi> by whom way is made for you <hi rend="blackletterType">boldly to come to the Throne of Grace, that you may find mercy;</hi> that is to ſay, for all you that having ſinned, feels the ſtroke of ſin, and forgets it not (as Sluggards do) and ſo in the ſence and godly ſorrow for ſin (in particular) attended with holy Reſolutions, with humble and hearty Confeſſion of the ſame, with fervent deſires, leading unto earneſt Prayer to God for the Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the ſame, <hi>you forgiving them that have treſpaſſed againſt you;</hi> and not onely this, for one thing is yet lacking, even, that you <hi rend="blackletterType">in Faith</hi> alſo commit your ſelves to his Grace, <hi rend="blackletterType">Believing</hi> that as he hath in mercy promiſed, ſo in faithfulneſs he will perform what he hath promiſed, even, the Remiſſion of ſins; <hi>for what things ſoever ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire when ye pray</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi rend="blackletterType">believe that ye receive them, and ye</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſhall have them,</hi> Mark 11.24. <hi>And who then can lay any thing to your charge? It is God that juſtifieth</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſuch; Who, (or what) is there then that condemneth? It is Chriſt that hath died? yea, rather that he is riſen again, who alſo maketh interceſſion for you</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">through Faith in his blood,</hi> Rom 3.25.</p>
               <p>Thus you being very ſerious and diligent in your Applications to God, <hi rend="blackletterType">laying hold</hi> on his Promiſes of Pardon and Remiſſion of ſin
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172158:11"/> by Faith, and ſo ſtanding alwayes juſtified by Faith, quitted and freed from all your ſins through Grace; have (ſo conſidered) no ground or plea, becauſe of your unworthineſs (being now made wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy in the Beloved, the Lord Jeſus) any longer to miſtruſt or que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion the good Will and Pleaſure of God, in reference to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from him the more ſpecial Diſcoveries and Operations of his Spirit, but may now boldly go to the Throne of Grace for the ſame, being ſuch whom God waiteth to be gracious unto, you having that Faith which his pleaſure is <hi>to account unto you,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">for Righteouſneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This being conſidered, how <hi rend="blackletterType">ſpeedily</hi> ſhould every Soul (not as a thing by the by, but) as their <hi rend="blackletterType">greateſt</hi> work, when at any time overtaken with ſin, to draw nigh unto God, and that in the <hi rend="blackletterType">ſence</hi> of every known ſin, with godly ſorrow for the ſame: not daring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, (heaping up ſin like the wantons) there being every way as much cauſe of Repentance and Faith for the latter ſins, as there was for the many former ſins committed in ignorance; which though perſons are ready to acknowledge, yet are (I fear) too apt to neglect the ſame, upon the account that they have renounced their former wayes, and their now being in the Way of God, and that Chriſt is now a Mediator for them, and the like; not conſidering that the Soul-ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying benefit of Chriſts Media orſhip is enjoyed according to mens Applications unto the Father by him: But O what comfort can a Soul have in any thing, or with what boldneſs ſhall he walk, talk, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf to his Bed, that having ſinned againſt his God, hath not as yee been with him, and ſo by Faith received a Pardon from him? True it is, that ſuch, while they neglect the great Soul-ſearching work, and are toſſed up and down with the cumbrances of this life, may have an <hi rend="blackletterType">imagined Peace and ſuppoſed Comfort,</hi> and ſo may go on (ſomewhat cheerfully) in their thoughts and thinkings, as if all were theirs; but alas! theſe (though they may talk of Gods Love and Mercy) are not able to ſay, upon ſure experience (with the Prophet) that <hi>the Lord hath</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">crowned them with loving kindneſs, and tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> Pſal. 103.4.</p>
               <p>O let him then that readeth underſtand, that every Soul that comes by Faith to be juſtified from their old ſins, have a great work to do, requiring much watchfulneſs, care and circumſpection, in order to their maintaining and keeping themſelves in a juſtified eſtate.</p>
               <p>But moreover, let men conſider, whether they do not (while wanting in their Applications to God for the Pardon of ſin) ignorantly go on in a way very dangerous, while the true Fountain of Grace is neglected; 'tis greatly to be feared, that they have <hi>hewed to themſelves broken</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:172158:12"/> 
                  <hi>Ciſterns that will not,</hi> yea, cannot anſwer their expectations; that is to ſay, perſons being made ſenſible that they have ſinned againſt God, have thereupon reſolved for the time to come to be more watchful, and to walk more wiſely before God; and then, having a little while in meaſure reformed themſelves, have <hi rend="blackletterType">thereby</hi> ſpoken peace to themſelves, thinking all is well: And why? <hi rend="blackletterType">Becauſe</hi> they are reformed: And thus do they, as it were, make their own works of Reformation, the ground of their peace and ſatisfaction. True it is, that works of Reformation in ſuch that have ſinned, is good, for the Lord calls for it; yet ſure I am (and I pray you to conſider it) that 'tis not that, no nor any work of Righteouſneſs that they can do; yea, though they ſhould for ever afterwards ſo exactly walk, both in words, thoughts and actions, as not again to ſin; yet I ſay, and confidently conclude, that 'tis not in the leaſt that, which can juſtifie or cleanſe them from the ſin already committed: And therefore it remains a work, none of the leaſt, for perſons that have ſinned againſt God, ſpeedily to draw nigh unto him, that by humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation (attended with holy reſolutions) and Faith, they may reach his promiſed Grace and Mercy, the onely ſure ground of peace and ſatisfaction; which whoſoever attains, may underſtandingly (with the Prophet) ſay, <hi>Return unto thy reſt, O my Soul, for the Lord hath dealt bountifully with thee:</hi> And ſo then (as perſons juſtified and quitted from ſin) are to endeavour (with calling upon God for his Grace to help them) ſome real and thorow Reformation, anſwering to their former reſolutions, (far exceeding what is, or can be in ſuch who neglect the true means of Juſtification) in which Reformation of theirs they may rejoyce, but not as imagining peace from thence, but rather upon the account that God is thereby more honoured, even, God who hath juſtified them from all their ſins.</p>
               <p>Now foraſmuch as 'tis Saints great work to keep themſelves in the way of Gods Grace and Mercy, that they may alwayes ſtand quitted and juſtified from ſin, without which they cannot go to the Throne of Grace with confidence to receive the ſpecial preſence of Gods Spirit; I would pray all ſuch (who are in the godly ſorrow, becauſe of their ſin) to weigh theſe following conſiderations, that henceforth there may be a more apt and ready cloſing in with Gods Promiſes, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to Pardon and Forgiveneſs of ſins.</p>
               <p>Namely, that the Lord, the Lord God againſt whom ye have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>is a gracious God, abundant in goodneſs, keeping mercy for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, forgiving iniquity, tranſgreſſion and ſin, plenteous in mercy, rich in mercy, abundant in mercy, that will abundantly pardon;</hi> all which the Scriptures witneſſeth.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:172158:12"/>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That God <hi rend="blackletterType">delighteth in mercy,</hi> Mic. 7.18. and <hi rend="blackletterType">taketh pleaſure in ſuch as hope in his mercy,</hi> Pſal. 147.11. and is <hi rend="blackletterType">full of compaſſion,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ready to forgive,</hi> Nehem. 7.19. but <hi rend="blackletterType">ſlow to anger,</hi> Pſal. 145.8.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That <hi>Gods mercies endureth for ever, and is from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting to Everlasting, to ſuch as keep his Covenant, reaching over all his Works, as the Heaven is high above the Earth,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo great is his mercy:</hi> even alſo as <hi>a Father pitieth his Children;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo the Lord pitieth them that fear him,</hi> Pſal. 103.11,13,17. Pſal. 145.9.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That God who <hi>ſpared not his own Son, but deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered him up for us all, will with him</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">freely give us all things,</hi> Rom. 8.32. <hi>For if when we were</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">enemies, we were reconciled to God by the death of his Son;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">much more ſhall we be ſaved,</hi> (and juſtified from ſin) <hi>by his being alive for evermore, making interceſſion for us,</hi> Rom. 5.10.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That notwithſtanding the great backſlidings of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> even <hi>playing the harlot with many lovers, upon every high Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and under every green Tree,</hi> and that <hi rend="blackletterType">after</hi> God had drawn near unto them in much mercy and love; yet even to them <hi>after they had done all theſe abominations, ſaith the Lord, the gracious God,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">turn thou unto me,</hi> Jerem. 3.1,6,7. And that in a day when they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led not for mercy, even then ſaid the Lord, <hi rend="blackletterType">return O backſliding Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, for I will be merciful, and not keep anger for ever,</hi> v. 12. Much more therefore will God extend his mercies unto ſuch who mourn in the ſence of their ſins, and call upon him for mercy whereby to be healed.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That to believe the Record of God touching the forgiveneſs of ſins, is <hi>a ſetting to our ſeals that</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">God is true,</hi> John 3.33. But contrariwiſe, not to believe, <hi>is</hi> (as much as in us lyes) <hi>a making</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">God a lyar,</hi> 1 John 5.10,11.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That <hi>if we confeſs our ſins, God is juſt and faithful to forgive us our ſins,</hi> 1 John 1.9. Shewing that we may as well queſtion the juſtneſs and faithfulneſs of God, as queſtion his readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to forgive the ſins of ſuch as confeſs the ſame: (but let none queſtion the neceſſity of Faith in order to the forgiveneſs of ſins, becauſe the Apoſtle here aſſures it to ſuch as confeſs their ſins, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt word concerning Faith; let none (I ſay) queſtion it upon that account, for by the ſame reaſon they may queſtion the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of <hi rend="blackletterType">Prayer,</hi> for that neither is mentioned in this place: To this therefore I ſay (as in many other caſes muſt be concluded) that it is ſuch that ſhall find mercy that are qualified, not only as ſaith
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172158:13"/> one Scripture, but as ſaith the Scriptures <hi rend="blackletterType">compared together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That we have an <hi>High Prieſt, paſſed into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, ſitting at the right hand of God,</hi> for that very end to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, even <hi>to ſave to the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">uttermoſt, by making interceſſion with his blood,</hi> Heb. 7.25. <hi>That ſpeaketh far better things than that of Abel,</hi> not for vengeance, but for mercy, for all ſuch as have <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith in his blood;</hi> and therefore (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Let us come</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">boldly to the Throne of Grace, that we may obtain</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That we have not ſuch an <hi>High Prieſt, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be touched with the feeling of our infirmities, but was in all points tempted like we,</hi> Heb. 4.15. <hi>and being tempted, he is able to ſuccour them that are tempted, for he is a</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">merciful High Prieſt, to make re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation for the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſins of the People,</hi> Heb. 2.17,18. <hi>God knoweth our frame, he remembreth that we are duſt,</hi> Pſal. 103.14.</p>
               <p>Conſider alſo, That in thy deſiring of God the bleſſing of Remiſſion of ſins, thou deſireſt not more of him, than what he did freely for thee, <hi rend="blackletterType">before</hi> thou deſiredſt it of him; yea, when thou waſt an enemy to him.</p>
               <p>And with theſe Conſiderations conſider, That if you ſhall diſtruſt his mercy, it renders you altogether uncapable to pleaſe God; <hi>For without</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Faith 'tis impoſſible to pleaſe God, for he that cometh to God,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">muſt believe that he is, and that he is a Rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From theſe and ſuch like conſiderations, how may you be encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged to throw your ſelves upon Gods Grace, rejecting all fleſhly ſtaggerings at the Promiſes of God through unbelief, that you may receive what is promiſed by Faith in the Promiſes, even the ſure and certain Pardon of all your ſins; that the hands which have hung down by reaſon of ſin laying upon the Soul, may be lift up with prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to God, and the feeble knees now made ſtrong and lively, in the true ſence of the Fathers love ſhining to the Soul; and then, Oh! then, with what boldneſs, courage and confidence may you go to God for the manifold Operations and Diſcoveries of his Holy Spirit, your ſins being pardoned, and your iniquities waſhed away by Faith in Chriſt? What ſtate or condition is there, that poſſibly you can fall into through the utmoſt rage, either of the world or Satan, or both, wherein there is not a Promiſe of God, either to be delivered out of it, or wonderfully to be ſupported and comforted in it? All which Promiſes lyes before, as tendred to ſuch that by Faith are juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from ſin, whereon they by Faith, may <hi rend="blackletterType">take hold,</hi> and ſo therein rejoyce for evermore, in all conditions.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:172158:13"/>
               <p>If at any time the believing man fall into calamity and great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, he preſently conſiders where his Refuge is, and believes in God, who hath ſaid, that <hi>he will be with his People in all their troubles;</hi> and ſo (during his continuance in the tribulation) he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periences the truth of that <hi rend="blackletterType">within himſelf,</hi> which he hath read was in others, even, <hi>tribulation working patience</hi> (in him) <hi>and patience, experience</hi> (in him) <hi>and experience, hope</hi> (in him) <hi>which makes him</hi> (bold, and) <hi>not aſhamed,</hi> before all thoſe that trouble him, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. and at length (poſſibly) is delivered from all his troubles, and ſo made able to ſay (with the Prophet) <hi>I truſted in the Lord, and he hath delivered me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If at any time the believing man, through the unexpected events of things, come to be clouded with many piercing cares, and Soul-vexations: he conſiders that 'tis written, we ſhould <hi>caſt all our care</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">upon God, for he careth for us,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.7. And through Faith he receives this word (and ſo it becomes to him an <hi>engrafted word,</hi> planted in his underſtanding) concluding that he, having on his ſide a word from God to care for him, hath more on his ſide to free him from thoſe piercing cares, than if all the world were joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for his freedom; ſo mightily doth he magnifie Gods Word in his heart: Thus he believingly commits all, and caſts all his cares upon God; and while others onely talk, and read of being careful for nothing, this <hi rend="blackletterType">believing man experiences the condition,</hi> being ſupported in his ſerious conſideration, that God who hath declared himſelf willing to care for his People, is every way more able to care for them, than they for themſelves: And alſo how unſafe it is for them to truſt to, or lean upon their own underſtandings, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer experiences ſufficiently declare; therefore this man believing in God is delivered, and cared for by God, and ſo made able to ſay <hi>what the Lord hath done for his Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If at any time, by reaſon of Wars, and rumours of Wars, or the great frowns of great men, many fears ſhall aſſault the believing man, he well remembers that theſe things muſt firſt be before the poſſeſſion of the Kingdom, and he (while others that are not in <hi>Davids</hi> integrity, and ſo not in his Faith, yet talks much of his words, but out of his life:) I ſay he, even the believing man truly in both <hi>Davids</hi> Integrity and Faith, in <hi>Davids</hi> words boldly ſaith, <hi>The Lord is my Light, my Strength, and my Salvation, of whom ſhall I be afraid? though an Hoſt ſhould encamp againſt me, my heart ſhall not fear, though War ſhould riſe againſt me,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in this will I be confident,</hi> Pſal. 27.1,2,3.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:172158:14"/>
               <p>If the believing man at any time fall into reproaches &amp; perſecution for Chriſts ſake, by Faith he takes hold of the good and powerful hand of God to ſupport him, and in the greateſt of afflictions to comfort him: Faith ſo acquaints the Soul with the unſpeakable riches and glory of Chriſt, in the time of his ſuffering for him, as that (<hi>Moſes</hi>-like) <hi>he eſteems the reproaches of him greater riches than the pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon;</hi> ſo he endures the perſecution <hi>by Faith, ſeeing him</hi> (and his glory which he hath promiſed) <hi>even him who is inviſible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the believing man fall into temptation, he remembers how 'tis written, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. that <hi>God is faithful,</hi> and ſo <hi>will not ſuffer his People to be tempted above what they are able to bear:</hi> Which word (while among others onely talked of) this man embraces, often conſiders, upon it leans, and in it is comforted: not ſuffering the violence of the temptation, nor any unlikelineſs of deliverance by other means, to take the leaſt place in his heart (which is not an <hi rend="blackletterType">evil heart in departing from the living God,</hi> Heb. 3.12. <hi>but a</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">true heart, drawing nigh unto God,</hi> Heb. 10.22.) whereby that ſhould make the word of Promiſe of no effect, but rather conſiders, that <hi>God knows how to deliver the godly,</hi> (and that he is every way able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them) <hi>out of temptations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If at any time Trading fail, or loſs of Goods come, or Lands and Livings be taken away, and he that is the believing man there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by come to be indebted; yet he conſiders that Gods Promiſes fail not, though all theſe things ſomewhat frown upon him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhelters himſelf in Gods moſt holy Word, and waites patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by Faith, yea, though he may ſee little or nothing in ſight, yea, and no wayes able to conceive how he ſhall be in a capacity to live for the future, which more than a little will trouble fleſh and blood, (which would live by <hi rend="blackletterType">ſight</hi>) all which makes not him ſtagger, or if ſtagger he do, yet he falls not, but keeps cloſe to Gods Word, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies it greatly in his heart, knowing no reaſon why he ſhould more eſteem Gods Commandements, than his Promiſes; he therefore priſes them above Gold, yea, fine Gold, concluding that they are a more <hi rend="blackletterType">ſurer maintenance,</hi> than the poſſeſſing of Kingdoms; and ſo ſpeaks peace and much ſatisfaction to himſelf through believing, taking joyfully the loſs or ſpoiling of goods, rejoycing that he hath a merciful God on his ſide, that knows all his wants; yea, and that is able to make that little Pot of Oyl, which yet onely remains, ſo wonderfully to encreaſe, as that he therewith may be able both <hi>to pay his debts, and to live comfortably on the reſt,</hi> 2 Kings 4.2,7.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172158:14"/> Wherefore he makes it his great work, <hi>to ſeek firſt the Kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs thereof,</hi> being that which is required on his part, in the doing of which he believingly waits for the fulfilling of that promiſed on Gods part; namely, that <hi>he will add all ſuch things:</hi> being alſo encouraged in this his confidence with thoſe weighty conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations publiſhed by the Lord Jeſus, for that very end, to beget Faith in his Diſciples; namely, that <hi>God doth feed the Sparrows, and richly cloath the Lillies of the Field;</hi> and therefore ſurely will much more take care for thoſe that are his adopted children, for whom he ſpared not his own Son to do them good; and therefore (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle reaſoneth) moſt ſurely will with him (the mercy of mercies) freely give all other good things: Alſo this believing man conſiders, that if he ſhould care and carp, doing what poſſibly can be done, yet cannot add <hi>one cubit to his ſtature,</hi> as Chriſt witneſſeth; as his own former experiences witneſſeth; and as the apparent event and iſſues of mens carping cares and intemperate thoughts witneſſeth; therefore he with all ſeriouſneſs and readineſs of mind commits his condition to the gracious God, who hath promiſed never to leave nor forſake his People; ſo that he boldly prayes to God for his daily bread, and as confidently expects it of him, yea, and as certainly receives from him, which he receives with thankſgiving, being one of them that believes and knows the truth.</p>
               <p>And thus while others depend upon viſible things, and ſo have them (to wit, Lands, Livings, Tradings, Relations, Powers) often in their minds &amp; affections, and conſequently under many piercing cares, and Soul-vexations while depending thereupon; while others (I ſay) are thus, the believing man (whoſe dependance is not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on things that are ſeen, but upon the Lord) contrariwiſe hath the Lord often, and much in his mind (for men are apt to mind that which is their conſtant help) and ſo this man having the Lord much in his mind, is thereby wrought into his fear, kept tender of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and greatly affected with, and much deſirous of the much-wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted preſence of his good Spirit; and thus his mind, and the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of his heart is much in Heaven with God, in Faith praying unto him for the ſame, and much there expecting what in Faith he hath prayed for, and having received, much there alſo in prayſing his Name therefore; by all which he is become much heavenly-minded, ſpiritually framed, able to ſay (as they of old) <hi rend="blackletterType">My con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is in Heaven,</hi> (when others onely reads of it, and talks of it, but knows it not in themſelves) O therefore, how much more bleſſed is it to live <hi rend="blackletterType">by Faith</hi> than <hi rend="blackletterType">by ſight!</hi> it being both a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172158:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172158:15"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:172158:16"/> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">God exalting, and a Creature-comforting</hi> ſtate and condition.</p>
               <p>But why do I ſpeak theſe things? Not becauſe I think that any will ſay in words, that 'tis better to live by ſight than by Faith. But alas! What is it for men to acknowledge what is beſt, and yet ſtill abide in what is worſt? For I would pray you to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or no it be not ſome viſible thing in preſent being that gives you your hopes of daily bread, rather than the ſure Promiſes of God? Is it not both your words, and in your inward thoughts, that you hope to live comfortably, and to bring the year well about, in that you have either Lands in poſſeſſion as your own, or a good Farm, or good Trading; or good Friends, or the like? If not ſo, I would know what means then the uſual complaints, diſcontents, great fears and vexations of ſpirit, when at any time theſe outward things fail, or begin to fail? If your hopes did ariſe from the onely pure foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, to wit, Gods gracious Promiſes; Why then ſhould you be ſo diſquieted? For the decaying or failing (in meaſure) of theſe outward things, doth not make Gods Promiſes to be no Promiſes, he abideth faithful, <hi>and all his Promiſes are</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Yea and Amen in Chriſt:</hi> You indeed may ſometimes in the time of need, and in the day of trouble, pray unto God that he would give you daily bread, and that he would deliver you out of trouble (it being generally known that Saints ſhould do ſo) and from hence conclude that your dependance is upon God, and poſſibly you may be a telling others that you deſire; and Oh! how good a thing it is, to truſt in God, and rely upon him in all conditions, &amp;c. When alas! (and for the Lords ſake conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it) you all that while may be far from truſting in God indeed; and even ſuch who <hi>draw nigh to God with your mouths, when your hearts may be far from God,</hi> even depending upon, and truſting in things viſible, inſtead of a heatty believing in God whom you pray unto, with a ſerious and conſtant waiting upon him for to receive that which you have asked of him.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, as the Faith of the Faithful, renders them happy, and in all conditions comfortable; ſo the Unbelief of the Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, renders him miſerable, and in all conditions comfortleſs; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a moſt bitter root from whence ſprings many, yea, a very great multitude of corrupt branches, the fruit whereof hath ſo mightily corrupted the earth; for the purging of which there is but little hopes, till ſuch time the bitter root (to wit, Unbelief) be plucked up out of the hearts of the Sons and Daughters of men; which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining in the hearts of the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> kept them out of the promiſed Land; for although their ſins were many, bearing divers
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172158:16"/> names, yet by the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.19. 'tis ſaid, <hi>They entred not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe of their unbelief;</hi> as if that were the root or cauſe of all, (or moſt) of the reſt: And again, thoſe that did enter in, in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times were <hi>broken off, becauſe of unbelief,</hi> Rom. 11.20. In ſome certain places <hi>Chriſt did not do many mighty works, becauſe of their unbelief,</hi> Mark 6.5. Mat. 13.58. <hi>He that believeth not is condemned already, becauſe he believeth not in the onely begotten Son of God,</hi> John 3.18.</p>
               <p>For what (conſider I pray you) is the cauſe of mens ſo diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God by tranſgreſſion? <hi>Hath not Iſrael heard, doth not Iſrael know? Yes verily,</hi> they have both heard and known, <hi>but the Word preached doth not profit them, not being mixed with Faith in them that hear it,</hi> Heb. 4.2. They well know that they ſhould improve their time to the beſt advantage, ſometimes in the Cloſet in ſerious and ſober Meditations, ſometimes in ſolemn Prayer and Supplications to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od, and ſometimes in Praying with Faſting; but alas! Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief riſeth up, and too much keeps under the Light of Truth in their Souls, filling them with diſtruſtful thoughts, even, how then they ſhall live and maintain their Families, <hi>Wherewith to eat, and wherewith to put on,</hi> if thus they ſhould ſpend their time: And ſo it comes to paſs, that men too too much are found dwelling, as it were ſatisfied, in their own cealed houſes, while the Houſe of God wants perfecting, and much of its original Ornaments.</p>
               <p>'Tis well known, that Saints ſhould be <hi>rich in Good Works, willing to communicate, and ready to diſtribute:</hi> But Oh! How doth Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief choak the inward movings hereunto, poſſeſſing Souls with many fears, touching what may happen in the time to come, though at preſent they enjoy all fulneſs? and ſo <hi>the bowels of compaſſion are too much ſhut up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>'Tis well known, that Righteouſneſs and Juſt-dealing is comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the Lord; but ſaith the unbelieving Steward, <hi>I cannot dig, to beg I am aſhamed, and what then ſhall I eat, or what ſhall I put on?</hi> (being diſcharged of my place) Wherefore Unbelief drives him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſly to account with his Lord, even fifty, for that which was (in Righteouſneſs) a hundred meaſures, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.</p>
               <p>But I forbear inſtancing in Particulars, concluding that as living by Faith, is a God-honouring, and Creature-comforting ſtate and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo not to live by Faith, but by ſight, is a God-diſhonouring, and Creature-diſcomforting ſtate and condition.</p>
               <p>But having ſpoke ſomething touching the great uſe of Faith, with provocations thereunto, which probably may be for advantage to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172158:17"/> ſome: yet very poſſibly for diſadvantge to other ſome, for want of a wiſe underſtanding every thing in its place: Therefore in the next place, I do hereby warn, and ſtrictly charge all ſuch, who are carnally minded, who have ſo embraced this preſent world, as that the growing in the knowledge of Jeſus, is little minded by them, or regarded: and yet are apt to lean upon the Lord, and ſeem to be very confident, and (with <hi>Iſrael</hi>) ready to ſay, <hi>Is not the Lord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us?</hi> being as it were offended with thoſe that ſhall queſtion their condition, they think it ſo good, and therefore are ready to conclude (as ſome of old have done) <hi>that no evil ſhall come unto them;</hi> when alas! they are poor and miſerable; And all ſuch I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude as being none of them (while ſuch) whom I hereby perſwade to lean and ſtay upon God by Faith: Therefore, O ye ſluggards and carnal-minded men, think not to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you profeſs, and have practiſed ſome of the Ordinances of Chriſt, and ſtill do own them, that therefore you have ground to believe that Gods Promiſes reaches you, for this did <hi>Iſrael</hi> do, and the Church of <hi>Laodecea,</hi> who nevertheleſs were miſerable, and their leaning upon the Lord rendred of no effect, becauſe of their unworthy walking in other things.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you do (as well as others) acknowledge that it is not enough to come into the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Ordinances, and Church-fellowſhip, with a heavenly and ſpiritual walking therein to the glory of God, that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you; for alas! though you in words deny ſuch a condition, yet your converſation plainly declares to others (and to your ſelves alſo, if you would ſeriouſly heed it) that you own it: 'tis not mens ſaying, that there muſt be, nor their much talking of, a heavenly and ſpiritual walking in the Profeſſion, that proves them to be ſuch, even, heavenly-minded men, or ſpiritual walkers; to talk of Life, Light, Spirit and Power of Godlineſs, is now become a <hi rend="blackletterType">meer Form</hi> among men, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny getting the words, but have not the thing it ſelf; and ſuch are moſt apt to declare againſt others, even to ſlight and diſdain <hi>little ones that believe in Chriſt,</hi> calling them carnal, literal and low profeſſors; Yea, ſome of this ſort in the Apoſtles dayes, were grown up to ſuch height of ſpiritual pride and arrogancy, as that they thought <hi>Paul</hi> and the reſt of the Miniſters of Chriſt, did <hi>walk after the fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.2. and ſo they looked upon their <hi>bodily preſence weak, and their ſpeech contemptible,</hi> ver. 10.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you walk honeſtly
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172158:17"/> among men, ſo as to abſtain from groſs and publick evils, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Promiſes of God reaches you; for all this you may do, and continue ſo, and yet go to Hell among the <hi rend="blackletterType">unprofitable ſervants, that have not gained by trading with the Talent committed unto them:</hi> this kind of common honeſty you have poſſibly for a long time manifeſted in your converſations; But where are the <hi rend="blackletterType">fruits</hi> that God juſtly looks for to be brought forth in the Power and Light of his Grace? If you know theſe things, and can talk of them; happy ſhall you be if warned by them.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you aſſemble with the Saints at their meetings, that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you; for ſo did <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yea, they ſeemed <hi>to take delight in approaching before God, to tread his Courts,</hi> Iſ. 58. Whoſe practiſes nevertheleſs was not regarded by God; neither may yours, being (poſſibly) to prevent the reproof of men, more than Gods; or at beſt to remove trouble of Conſcience, which ſometimes poſſibly you have undergone for neglect of meetings, but now frequenting them, you <hi rend="blackletterType">thereby</hi> ſpeak peace to your Souls, though for years you experience no advantage, or Soul-profit reaped thereby (which is the true end of meeting) a true Teſtimony (O ye) that your ſatisfaction is not in the right thing.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you confeſs your ſins and iniquities before the Lord, that therefore the Promiſes of God reaches you; for you may in words confeſs ſin, having at that time little or no ſence, either what ſin you have committed, or when committed; and ſo your words of confeſſion may proceed rather from a notion that ſuch a thing is ſpoken of in the Scriptures, and that others do ſo, than from a ſpirit wounded with the ſtroke of ſin, and broken in the <hi rend="blackletterType">deep ſence</hi> of ſin, from whence the words ſhould flow; and ſo having made confeſſion of ſin, preſently imagine that all is well, ſpeaking peace to your ſelves, barely becauſe you have ſpoken words as Saints did formerly, and now do; but alas! are far from ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any real ground to ſay (with the Prophet) <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, for the Lord</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">hath forgiven thee all thine iniquities,</hi> Pſal. 103.2,3.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you pray ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, both publick and private, that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you; for many and long Prayers were found among the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who nevertheleſs were <hi>a ſinful Nation, laden with iniquity,</hi> Iſa. 1.15,4. And ſo may you be notwithſtanding your many Prayers, and that not onely upon the account of your unworthineſs in other things, but alſo upon the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172158:18"/> account of imperfection (or rather corruptions) that may be in theſe your prayers (ſuppoſed by you the beſt of your performances) for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of ſpeaking words of Prayer, proceeding from a ſerious ſence of the want of Grace, which flowes from a great deſire to honour God, becauſe of its love to God; I ſay, inſtead of this kind of ſenſible praying to God, which is alwayes attended with (as its conſtant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion) a ſerious and conſtant waiting to receive from God, what is prayed for; alas! there may be by you words uttered proceeding from a meer notion, which may be exerciſed (as upon narrow ſearch may be ſeen) <hi rend="blackletterType">to find out words and expreſſions,</hi> and <hi rend="blackletterType">to utter them</hi> in ſuch a way &amp; manner, as may to the eyes and ears of men render <hi rend="blackletterType">you fervent and zealouſly affected</hi> after the things prayed for, rather than from any real and internal ſence begotten in you of God, leading you up nearer to God; your words (may be) importing more longings after Grace, than really is in you, and greater deſires, and larger affections after the Wiſdom and Power of God, than (indeed and in truth) is in you; your words (may be) importing alſo more dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of ſin and tranſgreſſion, than may be true from your hearts; and if ſo, What ſhall I ſay of this? Is it an acceptable ſervice in the ſight of God? Nay, it is in truth, a ſpeaking lyes before the Throne of Grace; a dead work timely to be repented of.</p>
               <p>Moreover, when you for ſome time neglect Prayer, probably are ſomewhat troubled; but then coming to a more frequent practice thereof, you <hi rend="blackletterType">thereupon</hi> put the trouble from you, and ſeem to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, though for a long time you experience no anſwer to your Prayers; which proves that your ſatisfaction is not in that which is bread in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: Yea, doth it not prove, that either yet you have not attained un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the New Birth; or if you have, that it is now even languiſhing, and almoſt ſenceleſs? for that (if in health) will not be ſatisfied with asking for the bread which is from above, unleſs it alſo receive it: no more than the birth which is after the fleſh, will be ſatisfied with asking for outward bread, unleſs it be alſo received, and enjoyed within.</p>
               <p>Moreover, when you joyn with others Praying in publick, it may be a ſmall occaſion, as a perſons coming in, or going out, or the like trifles, preſently cauſes the ear to liſten, and the eyes to gaze up and down; which if ſo, account not that an acceptable approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to God: What, no more reverence in ſpeaking to the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? No more ſence of your conditions, and of the neceſſity of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from God, to keep your minds more cloſe to God? In the true fear of God conſider theſe things.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you ſometimes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172158:18"/> praiſe God, and give thanks unto his Name; that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you; for this may you do (as <hi>Iſrael</hi> did) and yet far from that kind of praiſing God, which God accepts of, and which glorifies his Name: which proceeds from a true knowledge and ſence of mercies received, and ſo hearty deſires thereupon to ſet forth his praiſe: you being (it may be) onely led forth to ſpeak words of praiſe (poſſibly the very ſame, which the ſenſible man doth) from a naked apprehenſion that ſuch a thing is ſpoken of in the Scriptures, and that others do ſo; and therefore you cannot quiet Conſcience, unleſs you do ſo too: and it may be herein alſo utter expreſſions importing a greater and larger receiving from God, than indeed and in truth you have received; which to do, is hypocriſie and iniquity.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, becauſe you ſometimes read the Holy Scriptures, that therefore (with what is above ſaid) you have ground to believe the Promiſes reaches you; for ſo did the ſinful Jews do, yea, &amp; thought that they had in the Scriptures Eternal Life; who nevertheleſs were ſuch to whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>How can ye believe, that receive honour one of another?</hi> John 5.39,44. And may I not ſay to you touching this your practice, as touching the reſt of your performances? That is to ſay, when you read not, then are you diſquieted; but when you ſometimes read; then the trouble is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved and you at quiet, though little or no experience of profit rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped thereby, which is the proper end thereof: ſhould you not (even as your principal care) when you read Commandements, have an eye open within to ſee whether you have obeyed them, and kept cloſe to them, yea, or nay? And when you read Promiſes, to conſider whether you have or ſtill do believe them with all the heart, yea, or nay? Moſt ſurely this becometh ſuch as wait for the real ſubſtance of things.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, Becauſe when you at any time ſin againſt God, you can remember that there was ſomething within you that teſtified againſt the ſin, and oppoſed it; and ſo judge your ſelves in <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, <hi>Who did that which he would not;</hi> that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you, as well as they did <hi>Paul;</hi> for alas! how great may be your miſtake herein, the ground of your confidence, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, it may be no more than what the Drunkard may have to ſay, that he is in <hi>Pauls</hi> condition, who purpoſing to go to a merry meeting, is warned by his Friend not to go, who neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with full purpoſe of heart goes, and is drunk with the drunken;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172158:19"/> yet may he ſay, and truly too, that he was warned not to go, and that his friend oppoſed it; which (may be) is all you can ſay, even that the Word of God in your hearts, teſtified againſt the ſin which you were tempted unto; who nevertheleſs with full purpoſe of heart committed the ſin, without the drawings back, and contradictions of any regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate part in you, but onely the knowledge you have that ſuch and ſuch things are ſin and evil, contradicted it; which even the wicked and abominable in ſome meaſure have: Which if ſo, you are not able to ſay with <hi>Paul,</hi> from ſure experience, that <hi>your inward man</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">delighted in the Law of God, Rom,</hi> 7.22. <hi>And that you were</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">carried captive to the evil, by the Law in the members,</hi> ver. 23. <hi>And that you were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">with ſin, Gal.</hi> 6.1. And not that <hi rend="blackletterType">you</hi> overtook ſin; though poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly you may have theſe words in your mouths; but alas, if they are not true as to your condition, you do but deceive your ſelves thereby, <hi>thinking your ſelves to be what you are not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, Becauſe you do nothing but that you are able to ſhew ſome ſeeming ground and reaſon for your ſo doing; that therefore you have ground to believe Gods Promiſes rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches you; for that you may be able to do (as could <hi>Saul</hi> and the people with him for their ſparing the beſt of the Sheep and Oxen) and yet nevertheleſs <hi>live after the fleſh;</hi> the which whoſoever doth, ſhall die eternally. My meaning in many caſes of this nature, more clearly you ſhall underſtand by this one inſtance; namely, A certain carnal man, beholding a very new and curious faſhion in matter of Apparel, preſently falls in love with it, enters into Bed, and commits Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery therewith; but having received ſome Light from the Word, that Saints ſhould not faſhion themſelves according to their former luſts, and alſo living (poſſibly) among a people that are ready to reprove ſuch faſhions: Hereupon is led forth by the hand of the old corrupt man, to ſearch for ſome reaſonable account that may be given, both to himſelf (a little troubled through the Word bearing teſtimony againſt it) and alſo unto others; and while ſearching with this corrupt mind (Satan being not wanting) he findes that in ſome reſpect this new faſhion may be profitable (whereat he is glad) and ſo haſtily caſts out all former queſtions, and ſo procures it (though it coſt him a great deal more, than at any time he is willing to beſtow on the poor) and then with a loud voice, and much carnal diſputings, he ſtands to plead for it, for (ſaith he) 'tis thus and thus profitable, which poſſibly may be true in ſome ſmall ſenſe: But alas he conſiders not how <hi>the luſt firſt</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">conceived in him,</hi> by his aſſent with love and delight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: He conſiders not, that though there be ſome ſmall profit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172158:19"/> that 'twas not <hi rend="blackletterType">that which lead</hi> him to get it; for 'twas the love, and heart-delight which he had to it, as being a faſhion pleaſing the eye of fleſh, and whereby he might ſeem to others to be thus and thus; that firſt moved him thereunto. The worldly man will ſay, that he muſt ſpend much time, and take a great deal of care, to get this Worlds goods, that he may have ſomewhat conſiderably to give to the poor; but he lies in his heart before God and men.</p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves, Becauſe you ſometimes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute ſomething to the poor Saints, that therefore Gods Promiſes reaches you; for alas, ſometimes that may be onely a matter of <hi rend="blackletterType">con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint,</hi> and not willingly, and ſo not rewardable: I mean by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, ſo as that you may rather than you will publickly oppoſe ſuch and ſuch works of Charity, whereby you may think that people will ſpeak hardly of you, and you thereby come to have an ill name; rather than this, you may be conſtrained to give ſomething, though little or no heart to it otherwiſe: and ſometimes upon the account, that conſcience with ſuch a loud voyce calls for works of Charity, you may be perſwaded to part with ſomething to quiet conſcience, having all that while but little real and hearty love and compaſſion on the poor Saints; as appears (among ſome:) Firſt by their being quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and altogether ſatisfied, in that they have diſtributed ſomething; never conſidering whether they have done what is their duties to do, whether the poor Saints have food and raiment ſufficient, yea, or nay. Secondly, As appears by their much more diligent eye over ſuch as are poor, than over others; whereby to find ſome kind of flaw or other in their walkings, that ſo they may quiet conſcience thereby, while they adminiſter not to them; this ſavours of much carnality where ever it is, for ſhould you not <hi>be merciful, even as your Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Father is merciful?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves (ſome of you,) Becauſe you are more kind, milde, and more meek than others, that therefore the Promiſes of God reaches you: For although theſe things be good qualifications, yet may be no certain teſtimony to you of your ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and labouring in the grace of God, whereby theſe qualifications in you may be truly ſaid to be the fruits of the Spirit; though they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found in others may be ſo, yet (I ſay) not in you, becauſe it is but the ſame which was alwayes in you naturally; and you in the mean while may be far from it, and a great ſtranger unto any experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Conqueſt, and victory (through Divine help) over thoſe other Paſſions that have reigned in you, to the great diſhonour of God. Oh that you would remember Chriſts words, as thus, <hi>Every</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172158:20"/> 
                  <hi>Branch in me that beareth not fruit, God</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">taketh away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither think to ſay within your ſelves (ſome of you,) Becauſe you are able to preach, and to diſpute for Truth, that therefore you have ground to believe the Promiſes of God reaches you; for all this may you do, (<hi>as ſome of the Jews that were become Teachers of others, but were not taught themſelves</hi>) and yet at laſt may be inexcuſable, (as they were) while the life of Godlineſs preached to others, is not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved up to by your ſelves: For alas, what availeth it men to Preach unto others, that they muſt be new Creatures, if in the mean while they themſelves have not put off <hi>the old Man with his Deeds?</hi> And with what comfort or boldneſs can men Preach to others, that they <hi>ſhould Repent, Believe, and be Baptized for the Remiſſion of ſins, and ſo ſhall receive the gift of the holy Spirit;</hi> if in the mean while they know not their own ſins remitted, nor the gift of the holy Spirit received? Or with what comfort can any Preach the Goſpel of the Kingdom of Chriſt to others, if they in the mean while know not themſelves out of the Kingdom of Darkneſs, and ſo have themſelves (by faith) inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Kingdom of Chriſt? What, men talk, talk of life and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory, and in the mean while, do the works that leads unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to eternal death? Oh horrible blindneſs! Oh what a lamentable condition is this! How great is the diſproportion betwixt it, and the condition of the Goſpel-Preachers in dayes of old, who perſwaded others to have fellowſhip with them (ſaying) <hi rend="blackletterType">Truly our fellowſhip is with the Father, and with his Son Ieſus Chriſt?</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3. And ſo were ſuch as were able to tell others <hi>what the Lord had done for their ſouls; how God had comforted them in all their tribulations, and ſo were made able to comfort them which were in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith themſelves were comforted of God.</hi> 2 Cor. 1.4.</p>
               <p>Theſe things write I unto you, not becauſe I ſlight you, (under what name or Title ſoever you are, on whom theſe words may take hold) neither for your deſtruction do I thus ſpeak; but rather deſire you, and (with the holy Spirit ſpeaking to the Churches) do I hereby exhort you (O <hi>Laodiceans</hi>) timely <hi>to repent, and be zealous,</hi> that <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo</hi> Gods Promiſes may reach you, as well as any other; (for the Lord is not willing that any of you ſhould periſh) and that ſo his people may with all freeneſs have fellowſhip with you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:172158:20"/>
               <head>The great Errour and miſtake of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> concerning the true Chriſt; and how he is ſaid to be in his People: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Rule of Man-kind.</head>
               <p>MOreover, Since 'tis not the Talker, nor ready Diſputer, nor the Buſie Preacher of this World; but the ſingle-hearted doer of what is Preached, Diſputed, or Talked of, that ſhall enter into the Kingdom: It remains a work very great, for every Profeſſing Soul to abide very circumſpect and watchful, together with a conſtant truſting in, and dependance upon the Lord, (who waits to be gracious) that thereby they may be more and more wrought up unto <hi>a well-pleaſing the Lord in all things.</hi> But leſt any ſoul ſhould be deceived by the ſubtilty of the evil One, <hi>of whoſe deviſes</hi> (through grace) <hi>I am not altogether ignorant:</hi> I hereby alſo preſent before you the experiences of ſome men, as thus:</p>
               <p>Certain men being ſomewhat troubled about their preſent conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and thereupon following after a more excellent eſtate, (though poſſibly not with that care and watchfulneſs, as was meet ſhould be) have on a ſudden been greatly carryed forth with inward Power and Zeal, and wonderful quicknings after <hi rend="blackletterType">ſome</hi> matters of holineſs, ſo as ſcarce able to bear with the leaſt appearance of Pride, Covetouſneſs (or the like) in others, without reproof; yea, ſcarce content without a leaving their Callings in order to the reproving others; who at length (while in this ſtate) have been ſecretly informed, That the powerful workings within them, was Chriſt come in them the ſecond time to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; he being a Spirit, and not man, and ſo no other coming to be looked for but within; and that the Scriptures was not the Rule; and that the Ordinances of Chriſt were ceaſed, being impoſed onely till the time of Reformation, which time was come; and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>But being ſomewhat fearful of deluſions, did thereupon give up themſelves diligently to pray unto the Lord, who at length graciouſly delivered them from the ſtrong deluſion: I ſay, the ſtrong deluſion; for is it not ſo indeed, when an evil ſpirit ſhall carry forth perſons zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, to <hi rend="blackletterType">ſome</hi> things that is Juſt, Holy, and Good, (though he no lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of Holineſs or any Goodneſs; but that being really an Angel of Darkneſs, he may ſeemingly appear to be <hi>an Angel of Light,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14.) thereby to <hi rend="blackletterType">gain their affections?</hi> That then having got the affections, he may the better drop into their underſtandings, Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Errour in matters of Faith, with likelineſs of acceptance.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:172158:21"/>
               <p>Whereupon (dear Brethren) as I have here briefly propoſed to you the ready and plain Way in order to the Life of godlineſs, without which, all profeſſion thereof is little; together therewith I hereby alſo counſel you (in the words of <hi>John</hi>) <hi>not to believe</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">every ſpirit, for there are many falſe ſpirits gone out into the world;</hi> the one and true Spirit of God, being plainly to be known by his guiding and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Saints, not onely to be Juſt, Holy and Zealous in point of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; but alſo to be ſtedfaſt in the Principles of Faith, yea, and as <hi rend="blackletterType">zealouſly</hi> to contend for the ſame, as for any other things: as was the Apoſtles of Chriſt, in whom the true Spirit of Light was, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by their Writings, for that a great part of it conſiſts of matter tending to the inſtruction and regulation of the Saints, concerning their Faith, as in reading is obſervable: Wherefore, for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving all doubts and ſcruples which (through the ſubtilty of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived <hi>Quaker</hi>) poſſibly may ariſe, or already is riſen in the hearts of any well-minded people, I here next offer a little of that much, which might be ſaid, touching Principles of Faith, the errour where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is abundantly dangerous.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Whereas 'tis owned by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> (and as to me hath plainly been declared) that the Eternal Spirit of Light and Power which dwelt in the Man whom the Jews Crucified, is the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world; and not the Man that was Crucified, that was ſeen with viſible or carnal eyes; according to which you may obſerve the words of <hi>Wolrich</hi> (the <hi>Quaker</hi>) in his Book, entituled, <hi>A De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration to the Baptiſts,</hi> pag. 13. ſaying, That Chriſt was <hi rend="blackletterType">never ſeen with any carnal eye, nor his voice heard with any carnal ear.</hi> And in the Book, entituled, <hi>Sauls Errand to Damaſcus,</hi> pag. 14. (the words of <hi>George Fox</hi> the elder, I ſuppoſe) 'tis ſaid, That the <hi rend="blackletterType">fleſh</hi> of Chriſt is a <hi rend="blackletterType">figure.</hi> And <hi>Joſeph Fuce</hi> (in his Book entituled, <hi>The fall of a great viſible Idol,</hi> pag. 14.) ſaith (by way of reproof to us) theſe words, The Baptiſts (ſaith he) make fleſh their Arm, and therefore look with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out to know Chriſt after the fleſh; although the Apoſtle ſaid, <hi>They were to know him ſo no more:</hi> (mark) <hi>thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Curſed be the man that truſteth in man, and maketh fleſh his Arm,</hi> Jerem. 17.5. (as if they were a curſed people that truſt in the man Chriſt.) Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (I ſay) this is aſſerted by them, I here offer ſeveral grounds from the Holy Scriptures, whereby to prove, that the Eternal Spirit which dwelt in the Man, whom the Jews Crucified; which Spirit the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles afterwards received in them, is not the Chriſt, the Saviour of the world; but the viſible man, to whom the Spirit was given, <hi>John</hi> 3.34. The offering it ſelf, (no figure, but the ſubſtance of figures) is the Chriſt of God.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:172158:21"/>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe that the Eternal Spirit <hi rend="blackletterType">never died,</hi> when nothing is more plain than that Jeſus Chriſt died, as appears by a Cloud of Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe the Apoſtles (with one conſent) declare that <hi>the Jews Crucified</hi> (that is faſtned to a croſs) <hi>the Lord Jeſus, the Lord of Glory,</hi> Act. 2.36. 1 Cor. 2.8. <hi>and killed the Prince of Life,</hi> Act. 3.15. Whom they crucified not, nor killed, if the Eternal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit that dwelt in the viſible man, be the Chriſt: and ſo the <hi>Quakers</hi> by this their opinion do as much as in them lyes, declare the Holy Apoſtles to bear falſe witneſs to the world concerning Chriſt: <hi>but let them be true, and every one of theſe men lyars,</hi> in the judgements of the Wiſe: But to evade this, ſometimes they will ſay (whereby to deceive) that the Jews did crucifie Chriſt, that was, they oppoſed and reſiſted the Spirit of Light <hi rend="blackletterType">within them,</hi> which they call Chriſt: and withal will ſay (whereby to deceive) that the Jews did Crucifie a man without; I ſay to deceive, becauſe that in their confeſſion of this, (which ſeems ſometimes to the Hearers to be ſufficient) they intend not the Truth, namely, that that viſible man whom the Jews crucified without, was the Chriſt; as appears by their own words above ſigned.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe that not onely the Apoſtles, but alſo Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by his Inſtitution of thoſe two Ordinances, Baptiſm, and the Lords Supper, hath plainly declared Gods Way, graciouſly provided for mans Redemption and Juſtification contrariwiſe, even, by a <hi rend="blackletterType">bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, blood-ſhedding, dead, buried and riſen Chriſt,</hi> as ſaith the proper ſignification of theſe Ordinances: neither of which is either proper or true in relation to the Eternal Spirit, who was (all may know) neither dead nor buried, and ſo not riſen again, nor broken, nor at any time ſhed blood; all which theſe Ordinances teſtifie concerning the true Chriſt: and ſo the <hi>Quakers</hi> by this their opinion are found alſo ſuch, who in effect do ſay, that theſe Ordinances of the Lord (which once they ſay were in being) were <hi rend="blackletterType">lying Ordinances,</hi> bearing falſe witneſs to the Saints, touching the Lord Jeſus; but to all ſuch as fear the Lord, <hi>Let them be true, and every one of theſe lyars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Becauſe not onely the Apoſtles, Chriſt the Son, but alſo God the Father himſelf, moſt plainly declared from of old by his Commandement, for the killing and ſlaying thoſe many Sacrifices, and ſprinkling the blood thereof, that Jeſus Chriſt ſhould be ſlain, and his blood ſhed, as the glorious ſubſtance thereof: all which part of the Fathers Law, was, and is of no effect; God thereby bearing falſe witneſs to the world; if the Eternal Spirt, which dwelt in the viſible
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172158:22"/> Man, and which the Apoſtles afterwards received in them, be the Chriſt, which Spirit never was ſlain, nor never had blood to ſhed: <hi>but let</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">God be true, and all theſe men lyars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, Becauſe he moſt plainly is ſaid to be the Chriſt, <hi>Ordained of God to be Judge of quick and dead, to whom</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">all the Prophets gave witneſs,</hi> he (I ſay) with whom the Apoſtles did <hi rend="blackletterType">eat and drink,</hi> and that <hi rend="blackletterType">after his Reſurrection from the dead,</hi> Act. 10.38,41,42,43. which muſt needs reſpect the viſible Man.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, Becauſe the true Chriſt blamed his Diſciples when they ſuppoſed him to be a Spirit, ſaying to them, <hi rend="blackletterType">Handle me, and ſee, for a ſpirit hath not fleſh and bones,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">as ye ſee me have,</hi> Luke 24.37,38,39.</p>
               <p>Seventhly, Becauſe the true Chriſt was ſeen with viſible and carnal (that is fleſhly) eyes; for 'tis written, <hi>the eyes of all them that were in the Synagogue were faſtned on him,</hi> (to wit, Chriſt) and ſure I am that the <hi>Quaker</hi> cannot imagine (from any ſhow in the Scriptures) that theſe had any other eyes, as inviſible and ſpiritual eyes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis ſaid alſo, that <hi>all they in the Synagogue were</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">filled with wrath, and thruſt him out of the City,</hi> Luke 4.20,28,29.</p>
               <p>Eightly, Becauſe he is declared in the Holy Scriptures, to be Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who was <hi rend="blackletterType">Circumciſed;</hi> which were alſo a falſe account, if the <hi>Quakers</hi> opinion were true, namely, That the Eternal Spirit in the Man, and not the Man, was the Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Ninthly, Becauſe the Eternal Spirit which dwelt in the Man Chriſt, which afterwards the Apoſtles received in them, is called <hi rend="blackletterType">another Comforter,</hi> and that by Chriſt himſelf, which would not come unto the Apoſtles, unleſs he (the true Chriſt) <hi rend="blackletterType">went away,</hi> John 14.16,17. 16.7.</p>
               <p>Tenthly, Becauſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt lift up his</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">eyes to Heaven, and</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Prayed to God his Father,</hi> John 17. Both the action and the manner thereof ſhewing, that the viſible Man is the Chriſt: And beſides, if the <hi>Quaker</hi> ſhall ſuppoſe that 'twas the Eternal Spirit in the viſible Man Chriſt that prayed, and that the ſame Eternal Spirit is one eſſence or being with God the Father, and Chriſt his Son, without diſtinctions; I then would demand of them two things; firſt, Who it was that the Spirit <hi rend="blackletterType">Prayed unto?</hi> And ſecondly, <hi rend="blackletterType">For what</hi> he prayed, or what he ſtood in need of?</p>
               <p>Elevently, The Eternal Spirit which was given to, and received by the viſible man, cannot be the Chriſt, that is in Engliſh <hi rend="blackletterType">Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,</hi> becauſe he is ſaid by the Apoſtle to be the <hi rend="blackletterType">Anointing with which</hi> the Saviour was anointed: as 'tis written, <hi>how God anointed Jeſus,</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:172158:22"/> (that is, the Saviour) <hi>of Nazareth</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">with the Holy Spirit,</hi> Act. 10.38. If the Eternal Spirit, as Spirit, was anointed, I would know with what, and wherefore?</p>
               <p>Twelfthly, Becauſe the true Chriſt, even <hi>Sions</hi> King, is ſaid to come <hi rend="blackletterType">ſitting and riding upon an Aſs, meek and lowly;</hi> who alſo in lowlineſs <hi rend="blackletterType">waſhed the Diſciples feet:</hi> all which proves that the viſible man is the true Chriſt, <hi>Zecha.</hi> 9.9. Mat. 21.5. John 13.14.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>Henceforth know we no man after the fleſh, yea, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him</hi> (ſo) <hi>no more.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> What <hi>Paul</hi> intends by theſe words I verily believe, but that Chriſt is departed from and without that outward body of fleſh, which once was viſible on Earth, and ſo not to be known after the fleſh; that is, not now having that body of fleſh, this indeed I believe not.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Becauſe that then, and upon the very ſame ground, we are to know henceforth none amongſt men to be the Children of God, but ſuch onely as are departed from, and without their outward bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of fleſh; and where thoſe men are, or what kind of men they are, I verily know not: I thus ſpeak, becauſe in like manner as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Henceforth we know Chriſt no more after the fleſh;</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo alſo</hi> he ſaith, even, in the ſame words, that <hi>henceforth know we</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">no man after the fleſh;</hi> if true in one, then in both: but that it is untrue in one, you have hereby a weight of reaſon forbidding; that the other is alſo untrue, conſider the Scriptures forbidding it: As,</p>
               <p>Secondly, Becauſe thoſe that were of the number of Gods Elect in Ages paſt, <hi>Waited for the Son of God from Heaven, who was</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the dead,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.4,10. Now ſure I am, that 'twas the viſible body of fleſh which was dead, and ſo raiſed from the dead, that which was raiſed from the dead, the Saints of God waited for; and therefore they ceaſed not to know Chriſt as having the body of fleſh, which once he had, though both they and we believe that 'tis glorified.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Becauſe the ſame Apoſtle that ſpeaks theſe words, is ſo far from ſuch an opinion of undervaluing the fleſhly body of Chriſt, as that he tells the Church, <hi>they were reconciled to God in the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">body of his fleſh through death,</hi> Col. 1.21,22. And ſurely, neither <hi>Paul</hi> nor the Church was at any time to ceaſe knowing or honouring, that through which they were reconciled to God, <hi>His fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood drink indeed;</hi> and although in one ſence it profited nothing; yet ſuch is it in another ſence, as that <hi>whoſoever eateth and</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:172158:23"/> 
                  <hi>drinketh the ſame</hi> (<hi>that is, believeth in the Lord,</hi> John 6.35.) <hi>ſhall never hunger nor thirſt;</hi> And therefore for the conſtant remembrance thereof, we have that Ordinance of Breaking Bread, which ſurely was never inſtituted to hold forth an <hi rend="blackletterType">unprofitable thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But true it is, That neither Chriſt nor men, are to be known after the fleſh; and how once men were known after the fleſh, is plain from the ſame Apoſtles words, as thus, <hi>We are the Circumciſion which worſhip God in Spirit, and have no confidence in the fleſh, wherein if any might truſt, I more</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul:</hi>) Now what he means by this, is manifeſt, to wit, <hi>being Circumciſed, of the Stock of Iſrael, of the Tribe of Benjamin, an Hebrew of the Hebrews,</hi> &amp;c. Phil. 3.3,4,5. But he well knowing that the Miniſtration of the Law (under which perſons were thus known after the fleſh) then done away, and a more glorious Miniſtration in being, which forbids men to plead, <hi>we have Abraham to our Father,</hi> we are his Children after the fleſh, of the Stock of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> of this or that Tribe; and therefore let us be Baptized and known among you (according as you may read the Phariſees did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.7,8,9.) <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſay, well knowing this, declared that he had no confidence in the fleſh, as in reference to himſelf; neither henceforth would he know any other man after the fleſh, as once during the time of the Law men were known and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, even, the Children of Promiſe (in reſpect of temporal enjoyments) being ſuch as deſcended from that fleſhly, birth-privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Seed of <hi>Abraham:</hi> Therefore (ſaith he) <hi>If any man be in Chriſt, he is a New Creature, the Seed of Abraham, according to the Faith of Abraham, either Jews or Gentiles:</hi> In like manner as there was a time when Chriſt was eſteemed and known, upon the account, or becauſe of his being born of the Tribe of Judah, and of the birth-priviledged Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> yet now henceforth (ſaith the Apoſtle) know we him (ſo) no more; that is, as to eſteem him upon that account, or for that reaſon <hi rend="blackletterType">meritoriouſly</hi> the Saviour of the world, but rather upon the account of his coming down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, his being the Son of God reconciling the world unto himſelf, in the body of his fleſh through death.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>The firſt man Adam was made a living Soul, the laſt Adam was made a quickning Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> True it is, that the Apoſtle thus ſpeaketh; but conſider how he is, or can be called the <hi rend="blackletterType">laſt Adam,</hi> or the <hi rend="blackletterType">ſecond Man</hi> (as afterwards he is called) if Chriſt be ſo a quickning Spirit, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as he was before the world was: for if the Spirit (as Spirit) be the laſt, or ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> then it follows that the firſt man <hi>Adam, who</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:172158:23"/> 
                  <hi>was of the earth, earthy,</hi> was <hi rend="blackletterType">firſt, and before the Eternal quickning Spirit;</hi> which were very abſurd to think: and therefore Chriſt of neceſſity muſt be underſtood to be the laſt <hi>Adam,</hi> upon the account of his being become viſible man, a condition that he was not alwayes in, but ſince the creation and fall of the firſt man <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo is truly and very properly the <hi rend="blackletterType">laſt or ſecond man, made a quickning Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit:</hi> yet not ſo a ſpirit in the Apoſtles ſence, but that he is alſo <hi rend="blackletterType">ſpiritual</hi> (ver. 46.) and alſo the <hi rend="blackletterType">man, by whom came the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the dead</hi> (ver. 21.) <hi>and alſo the Chriſt that</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">died, was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, and roſe again</hi> (ver. 3, 4.) and therefore not ſo a quickning Spirit, as in the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſence: for the Spirit conſidered as from Eternity was not man, and ſo was never dead, and ſo not buried, and ſo not raiſed again: all which <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifies in that very Chapter concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him, whom he calls a quickning Spirit, (in reference to his now being a <hi rend="blackletterType">ſpiritual glorified man</hi>) which conſidered, it remains, <hi>that all the Houſe of Iſrael know aſſuredly that God hath made that ſame Jeſus, whom the Jews Crucified, both</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Lord and Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, as the <hi>Quaker</hi> holds, That the Spirit which was in the viſible man (and not the man) was the Chriſt: So alſo he holds, and indeed it leads him to hold, that the ſecond coming of Chriſt is in men, and not otherwiſe; and therefore <hi>Humphrey Smith</hi> in his Book, entituled, A <hi>true and everlaſting Rule,</hi> pag. 19, 20. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares ſuch, who look after the body of Chriſt, to thoſe young men that ſought in vain the body of <hi>Elijah,</hi> and plainly ſaith, that ſuch (whom he calls wandring ſtars) ſhall <hi rend="blackletterType">never find the body</hi> they look ſo much after: he alſo ſpeaking of Chriſt, pag. 30. ſaith, That he is come, whom we long waited for, and we <hi rend="blackletterType">do not look for any other;</hi> who <hi rend="blackletterType">now</hi> (ſaith he) appears the <hi rend="blackletterType">ſecond time</hi> without ſin, to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that which was loſt; and ſo (ſaith he) we confeſs Chriſt come in the fleſh, and <hi rend="blackletterType">do not look for another,</hi> pag. 32.</p>
               <p>Now as their perſwaſions concerning Chriſt being a Spirit, and not man, leads them to expect the coming of Chriſt in them: ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe our Faith and full perſwaſions, that Chriſt is a viſible glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied man, leads us to expect his ſecond coming as a diſtinct appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from, and not in, his People; whereupon I forbear to urge thoſe many Scripture-grounds which with all plainneſs ane loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of voice reproves theſe mens <hi>ſwelling words of vanity,</hi> and ſhall onely ſpeak ſomething touching thoſe Scriptures, which ſpeaks of Chriſts being in his People, whereat ſome, for want of underſtanding, may poſſibly ſtumble.</p>
               <p>True it is, That the Apoſtle tells the Church of the <hi>Coloſſians,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:172158:24"/> 
                  <hi>that Criſt was in them, the hope of Glory,</hi> Col. 1.27. Yet not ſo in them, but that he could alſo ſay, and that at the ſame time, to the ſame Church, that <hi rend="blackletterType">when Christ who is our Life</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſhall appear, then ye ſhall appear with him in Glory,</hi> even, in the poſſeſſion of that Glory which then they had hopes of, ver. 3, 4. The Apoſtle alſo declares <hi>Chriſt to be in the Corinthians, except they were Reprobates:</hi> Yet not ſo in them, but that <hi>they were alſo</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">waiting for the coming of Chriſt,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.7. Yea, at that time when <hi>they were ſanctified in Chriſt,</hi> ver. 2. <hi>and in</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">every thing enriched by him, coming behind</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in no gift,</hi> ver. 5, 7. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo teſtifies concerning himſelf, <hi>That Chriſt lived in him;</hi> yet not ſo, but that he <hi rend="blackletterType">looked alſo for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Chriſt,</hi> Tit. 2.13. Yea, and at that time when <hi>he had finiſhed his courſe, and the time of his departure</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">at hand,</hi> he ſpeaks to <hi>Timothy</hi> of a Crown of Righteouſneſs, <hi>which the Righteous Judge</hi> (ſaith he) <hi rend="blackletterType">ſhall give me at that day, even, at</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">his appearing,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.1,6,7,8. The Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is come;</hi> that is, the <hi rend="blackletterType">firſt time;</hi> which <hi>John</hi> might well ſay, for he had <hi>ſeen him with his eyes, and handled him with his hands,</hi> 1 John 1.1. But Chriſt afterwards aſcended, from whom <hi>John</hi> received great things, yea, much of the ſpecial preſence of Gods Spirit mightily working with him; yet did he not ſay, that Chriſt was come the <hi rend="blackletterType">ſecond time,</hi> for himſelf (after thoſe many Viſions and Revelations we read of was diſcovered to him) readily prayed, <hi>even ſo,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">come Lord Ieſus,</hi> Rev. 22.20. <hi>Stephen</hi> a man <hi rend="blackletterType">full of the Spirit, yet looking</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">up into Heaven, teſtified that he ſaw</hi> (in Heaven) <hi>Jeſus Chriſt ſtanding at the right hand of God;</hi> and the truth of this, he ſealed with his blood, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.55,56,58.</p>
               <p>Moreover, as <hi>Paul</hi> bears witneſs of Chriſts dwelling in the Saints; ſo alſo he declares, that the Saints were in him, <hi>even, as it is meet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>for me to think this of you all, becauſe I have you</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in my heart,</hi> Phil. 1.7. And elſewhere ſaith, that <hi>you are</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in our hearts, to dye and live with you,</hi> 2 Cor. 7.3. Now 'tis out of queſtion, that the ſeveral perſons of the Churches were not in the Apoſtles heart, but onely they were deep in his affections, and much in the Thoughts and Meditations of his heart, even, <hi>ſo as to dye and live with them</hi> (he believing them to be the beloved of God) So the Saints, having Chriſt deep in their affections, much and often in their Thoughts and Meditations, (believing him to be their moſt precious Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, <hi>Who is gone into Heaven to prepare a place for them,</hi> John 14.2.) So, I ſay, Chriſt dwelleth in his People, <hi>or in the hearts of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by Faith:</hi> And this kind of Language is both proper and common
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172158:24"/> to this day, for perſons that are deep in each others affections, in their perſonal abſence one from another, to ſay that ſuch are in their hearts, or that ſuch are often in their mindes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, as 'tis ſaid, that Chriſt is in his Saints, ſo likewiſe 'tis ſaid, and that more frequently in the Scriptures, That the Saints are <hi rend="blackletterType">in Chriſt, and in God;</hi> as thus, <hi>Paul an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, unto the Saints, and faithfull Brethren</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in Chriſt that are at Coloſſe,</hi> ch. 1. v. 2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of the Theſſalonians, which is</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in God, the Father, and</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> ch. 1.1. <hi>Unto all the Saints</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in Chriſt Ieſus which are at Philippi,</hi> ch. 1.1. <hi>Unto the Saints and faithfull</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in Chriſt, which are at Epheſus,</hi> ch. 1.1. Now, that the Saints are <hi rend="blackletterType">in Chriſt,</hi> after the manner that theſe men plead for Chriſts being <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Saints,</hi> judge ye that fear the Lord and ſerve him with uprightneſs of heart; remembring that he is the true Chriſt, who was <hi rend="blackletterType">dead,</hi> but is alive for evermore, a Mediator betwixt God and Men, <hi rend="blackletterType">the man Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, hear what the Lord Chriſt ſaith, as a moſt clear reſolve to this caſe, as thus, <hi>John</hi> 17.21,23. <hi>Thou Father art</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in me, and I</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in thee, that they alſo may be one</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in us. I</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in them, and Thou</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in me, that they may be made perfect in one;</hi> compared with theſe his words, <hi>John</hi> 15.10. <hi>If ye keep my Commandements, ye ſhall abide</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in my love, as I have kept my Fathers Commandements, and abide</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">in his love.</hi> Moſt clearly ſhewing, that Chriſts being <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Father,</hi> is meant, <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Fathers love,</hi> as himſelf witneſſeth: and ſo the Fathers being <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Son,</hi> is meant, <hi rend="blackletterType">in the Sons love:</hi> ſo likewiſe our being in the Eather, and in the Son, is meant, <hi rend="blackletterType">in their love:</hi> So, even ſo Chriſts dwelling in the Saints, is meant, his dwelling <hi rend="blackletterType">in their love, in their affections</hi> (as hath been ſaid.) Now, whereas the Son was in the Fathers love, there was given unto the Son, from the Father, the Holy Spitit, (without meaſure) working <hi rend="blackletterType">in him,</hi> whereby he did <hi>the works that no man ever did,</hi> to the glory of the Father: So in like manner the Saints being in Chriſt, in his love and affections; there is alſo given to the Saints, (through Chriſt) the Holy Spirit (in meaſure) working <hi rend="blackletterType">in them,</hi> whereby <hi>the deeds of the body are to be mortified,</hi> Rom. 8.13. and the fruits of Righteouſneſs brought forth to the Glory and Praiſe of God, by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obj.</hi> From theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 14.16,17. <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">another Comforter, even the Spirit of Truth, whom the world cannot receive, becauſe it ſeeth him not, neither knoweth him: but ye know him, for he dwelleth with you, and ſhall be in you.</hi> From theſe words (I ſay) 'tis conceived, and declared by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that Chriſt that was then with the Diſciples, ſhould afterwards be in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:172158:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> He that hath an ear to hear, may eaſily underſtand, that he, who is ſaid to be with the Diſciples, and ſhould afterwards be in them, was not the Chriſt, but <hi rend="blackletterType">another Comforter,</hi> whom the Chriſt would pray to the Father for, even, <hi>the Spirit of Truth, whom the world could not receive, becauſe they ſaw him not,</hi> nor knew him to be the Spirit of Truth, from God, (though through him was done ſuch works as no man ever did,) yea, they were ready to ſay, that he had a Devil (in him) but the Diſciples knew him to be the Spirit of Truth, and acknowleged the mighty works to be done through the Spirit of God <hi rend="blackletterType">in him;</hi> therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ye know him, for he (the Spirit of truth, another Comforter,) dwelleth with you;</hi> (that is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Spirit, being in Chriſt, and ſo <hi rend="blackletterType">with</hi> the Diſciples, for he was not then given to them, as he was afterwards, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.37.) <hi>and ſhall be in you,</hi> that is, the Spirit of Truth, <hi rend="blackletterType">another Comforter;</hi> which, when Chriſt was exalted, <hi>having received of the Father the Promiſe of the Holy Spirit,</hi> he made good to his Diſciples, by ſending his Holy Spirit in them, which before was with them, being in Chriſt that was with them.</p>
               <p>Theſe men ſay, Chriſt is come in them the ſecond time, and they <hi rend="blackletterType">look not for any other;</hi> and withall have <hi>good words and fair ſpeeches,</hi> crying, Grace, grace, Light, light. But let all aſſuredly know, that they themſelves are not in the True Light, nor Grace of God that brings Salvation, wherein the Saints of old walked; for they thereby were <hi>taught to deny ungodlineſs and worldly luſts, and to</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">look for the glorious appearing of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Tit. 2.11,12,13. But ſaith <hi>Humphrey Smith,</hi> Chriſt is come, and <hi rend="blackletterType">we look not for any other,</hi> another voice from another Spirit.</p>
               <p>Moreover, the <hi>Quaker</hi> utterly denyes (as moſt men I ſuppoſe knows) the Holy Scriptures to be a Rule: whereunto <hi>Humphry Smith,</hi> in his Book intitlued, <hi>A true and everlaſting Rule,</hi> pa. 29. in the face of men and Devils affirmeth, That there is <hi rend="blackletterType">no other Rule, Wayes, Means, or Name,</hi> by which man ſhall ever come to walk with God, but by that which is manifeſt of God <hi rend="blackletterType">in him,</hi> which (ſay they) is ſufficient to guide in all the wayes of God without Scripture, or any other outward means.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> The time was, (and that not long ſince in our Nation) when it was no leſſe then ridiculous, and a matter of contempt, for men and women to go to the publick Place of their Worſhip, with the Bible under their Armes, whereby <hi>to ſearch whether thoſe things they heard were ſo or no:</hi> ſuch and ſo great was the Romiſh cloud of darkneſs then ſpread over the faces of the multitude, they being informed by their blind Guides, that Ignorance was the Mother of Devotion: But Satans device <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> diſcovered in this, and the Scriptures very generally ſearched into,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172158:25"/> he hath now found out another way, whereby to produce a low eſteem to the Holy Scriptures, even by his manifold endeavours to perſwade people that there is a Light placed in them, which is to be their Rule, and is ſufficient without the Scriptures, or any other outward means, to guide them in all the wayes of God; which being believed unavoidably leads people to have a low and ſlender eſteem of the Scriptures; and by this means it is become again a very rare thing to ſee (among theſe people called <hi>Quakers,</hi> when they are aſſembled together (the Book of the Holy Scriptures diligently ſearched, whether thoſe things ſpoken be agreeable thereunto, yea or nay: and thus the Miniſters of theſe people are hereby put into a capacity greatly to deceive their Hearers while in their preaching up their manifold Errours, they make uſe of (with their own) ſome Scripture Expreſſions alſo, ſeemingly favouring their Opinions, (but not really) as to inſtance; Say they in their Doctrine, Ordinances, to wit, Baptiſm in water, and the Lords Supper, are now ceaſed, for <hi>Chriſt hath blotted out the hand-writing of Ordinances that was againſt us, and nailed them to his Croſs,</hi> Col. 2.14. which being heard by the People, they remember well that they have read ſuch kind of words, and for the tryal thereof they (according as they have been taught) begin to look within them, to ſee what Teſtimony is there; now the Devil being a Spirit, and ſo working within, being alſo an Enemy to Chriſt and his Ordinances, he, even he bears teſtimony within them, that what they have heard is true, even that the Ordinances are ceaſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whenas thoſe that ſearch the Scriptures according to the commandment of Chriſt, quickly ſee, that 'tis the Ordinances of the Old Teſtament, and not of the New, that Chriſt <hi>nailed to his Croſs:</hi> Now if you obſerve theſe men, being firſt deceived concerning the Rule, thereby are greatly disinabled to deſcern the Evil ſpirit ſpeaking within them; for by what ſhould he be tryed, if the Scriptures be not a Rule? and ſo theſe (alas poor creatures!) finding ſuch and ſuch perſwaſions within them, greatly fear to contradict or gain-ſay it; it being no leſſe to them then to contradict or gain-ſay the mind of the Lord Jeſus, they believing that it is Chriſt the Light that ſpeaketh within them; yea although their inward perſwaſions never ſo much contradict the Scriptures, yet they adhere to them, not daring to queſtion the Light (as they call it) within them, but preſently concludes that they have underſtood the Scriptures, and ſo perverts the plain meaning thereof into ſome kind of (imagined) Myſtery, that ſo they may one way or other cauſe the Scriptures without to ſpeak agreeable to that they call Light within them: And that I wrong not theſe men hereby, conſider one thing of many that might be inſtanced, namely, touching Women, who in all plainneſs are forbidden (by the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:172158:26"/> Scriptures) to teach in the Church: but ſince the Spirit in theſe men ſayes, that women may teach, they adhere thereunto, and perverts the plain Scripture into a Myſtery, and ſo declares, that the woman which is forbidden to teach (1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12,13.) is the wiſdom of the fleſh either in man or woman, and not the Female kind, as you may read in <hi>Farnworths</hi> Book, intituled, <hi>A Woman forbidden to ſpeak in the Church,</hi> page 3.</p>
               <p>But that there is no ſuch Light in every man, as aforeſaid, appears in that Chriſt gave commandment to his Apoſtles, to <hi>go into all the world, and teach all Nations, to obſerve all things whatſoever he had commanded them,</hi> Marke 16.15. Mat. 28.19,20. And <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, that he had declared <hi>all the Counſel of God,</hi> Acts. 20.27. whereupon 'tis required, that men <hi>incline their ear, and hear, that their Souls may live,</hi> Iſai. 55.3. and <hi>ſuch as turn away</hi> their eares <hi>from the truth</hi> are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, 2 Tim 4.4. All which were empty and uſeleſs things, both Chriſts Command, That all things whatſoever ſhould be taught the Nations, the Apoſtles obedience to that Command in Preaching all things, and alſo the Nations lending their ears to hear what is preached to them; if it were true that there were ſuch a Light in every man of the Nations, as were ſufficient to guide in all the wayes of God, and were placed in the Nations for that very purpoſe, and that no other Rule, or Means could lead to God, (which <hi>Humphery Smith</hi> affirmeth) 'Tis indeed ſaid by the Prophet, that Chriſt ſhould be given <hi>a Light to the Gentiles,</hi> from whence theſe men plead, That Chriſt is a Light in every one of the Gentiles, without any other outward means: But <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> (well underſtanding the Scriptures) pleaded another thing from thence, directly contrary, namely thus, <hi>Lo, we turn to the Gentiles, for ſo hath the Lord commanded us, ſaying, I have ſet thee to be a Light of the Gentiles,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.46,47. becauſe 'twas ſaid, Chriſt was ſet to be a Light of the Gentiles, therefore they would go and preach to the Gentiles: And what were they to preach to them? not that one thing of turning to (a Light) their Teacher within, but <hi>ALL THINGS WHATSOEVER,</hi> Mat. 28.19,20. <hi>all the Counſel of God,</hi> Act. 20.27. I then (with the Apoſtle) conclude thus, <hi>How ſhall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they hear without a Preacher? and how ſhall</hi> they <hi>preach except</hi> they <hi>be ſent? How beautifull therefore are the feet of them that preach the Goſpel! So then, Faith cometh by</hi> hearing, <hi>and hearing by the Word of God,</hi> Rom. 10.</p>
               <p>Among many things contradicting this Opinion, That every mans Rule is within him, and that there is no other Rule, Means, or Wayes that leads to God: this is none of the leaſt, namely, Becauſe when there was asfair occaſions given, (as well can be conceived) for the Doctrine
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:172158:26"/> of turning to a Light within, to be preached; as fair occaſions I ſay, as well can be conceived, through the many enquiries of men, even <hi>what they ſhould do;</hi> that then 'twas not preached, neither by God, Chriſt, Angel, nor men; as to inſtance,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the dayes of the Prophet Zechariah, Sherezer and Regem-melech were ſent by the Children of Iſrael to enquire of the Prieſts and Propets which were in the Houſe of God, whether they ſhould weep in the fifth Month, ſeparating themſelves as they had done many years before?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But God ſpeaks by the Prophet, ſaying, <hi>Should you not hear the</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">Words which the Lord hath cryed</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">by the former Prophets, when Jeruſalem was inhabited, and in proſperity,</hi> Zech. 7.2,3,7.</p>
               <p>Alſo <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, who is declared to be a burning and a ſhining Light, ſent two of his Diſciples unto Jeſus, ſaying by them, <hi>Art thou he that ſhould come, or do we look for another?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But (ſaith the man Chriſt) <hi>Go, and tell</hi> John <hi>what things you have heard and ſeen, how that the blinde ſee, the lame walk, the Lepers are clenſed,</hi> &amp;c. ſuch outward means was returned by Chriſt, the true Light, for <hi>Johns</hi> ſatisfaction, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.19,20,21,22.</p>
               <p>In the Dayes of <hi>John</hi> came the people unto him, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do? alſo the Publicans, ſaying, Maſter, what ſhall we do? alſo the Souldiers demanded of him, ſaying, What ſhall we do?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith <hi>John</hi> (having another Spirit) <hi>He that hath two coats let him impart to him that hath none, exact no more then that which is appointed you, do violence to no man, neither accuſe falſly, but be content with your wages,</hi> Luke 3.10,11,12,13,14.</p>
               <p>Alſo a certain Young man came to Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>What good thing ſhall I do, that I may have eternal life?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Keep the Commandements, and ſell that which thou haſt, and give to the poor,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.16,17,21.</p>
               <p>Again the Jews demanded of Chriſt, ſaying, <hi>What ſhall we do, that we might work the works of God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith Chriſt, <hi>This is the work of God, that ye believe on him whom he hath ſent,</hi> that was Chriſt himſelf that talked with them, and was not <hi rend="blackletterType">in them,</hi> that afterwards dyed for the ſins of the World, <hi>John</hi> 6.28,29. <hi>Lord, What wilt thou have me to do,</hi> ſaith <hi>Saul?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:172158:27"/>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith the Lord Chriſt, (and this after his Aſcenſion) <hi>Ariſe, and go into Damaſcus, and there it ſhall be told thee of all things which are appointed for thee to do,</hi> and that not by a Light within him; for when he was come to <hi>Damaſcus, Ananias</hi> (a certain Diſciple) told him many things, as you may read; and ſaid, <hi>Why tarryest thou? Ariſe and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſins, calling upon the name of the Lord,</hi> Act. 22.10,11,12,13,14,15,16.</p>
               <p>Moreover, when Peter had preached many things to the People at <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> 'tis ſaid, <hi>when they heard</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">this, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid unto Peter, and to the reſt of the Apoſtles, What ſhall we do?</hi> and (ſaith the Jalour) <hi>What muſt I do to be ſaved?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith <hi>Peter, Paul,</hi> and <hi>Silas,</hi> (being led with the Spirit of Light indeed) <hi>Repent, Believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and be baptized every one of you in his Name for the Remiſſion of Sins; and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Spirit,</hi> Act. 2.37,38. Act. 16.30,31.</p>
               <p>In like manner when the Angel of God appeared in a viſion unto <hi>Cornelius,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>What is it Lord?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Turn to the Light within (ſaith the <hi>Quaker.</hi>)</p>
               <p>But ſaith the Angel of Light, <hi>Send men to Joppa, and call for one Simon, who is ſurnamed Peter, he ſhall tell thee what thou oughteſt to do;</hi> and when <hi>Peter</hi> was come, he preached unto him Chriſt, whom the Jews ſlew, and hanged on a tree, with whom they had eat and drank, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and at length ſaid, <hi>Can any man forbid water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, and he commanded them to be baptized,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.4,5,6,38,39,41,47,48.</p>
               <p>Object. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, That <hi>the anointing which ye have received, abideth in you, and ye need not that any man teach you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Conſider, The Churches unto whom the Apoſtles wrote their Epiſtles, were gifted with the Holy Spirit, the anointing, as themſelves acknowledge in their Writings; yet nevertheleſs, they ſaw need for them to write: but it appears that this Church, or Churches, to whom <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks theſe words, were ſo enriched with ſpiritual gifts, ſo many gifted Brethren among themſelves, in whom the anointing ſo mightily wrought, as that <hi>Iohn</hi> doth as it were ſay, that <hi>theſe things I have written indeed unto you concerning them that ſeduce you,</hi> but I look upon you ſo furniſhed with the gifts of Wiſdom and ſpiritual Underſtanding, as that there was no abſolute neceſſity for any man, either I <hi>Iohn, Peter,</hi> or <hi>Paul</hi> in remote places,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:172158:27"/> to write unto you, whereby to inſtruct and teach you: Furthermore, the anointing abode indeed in them, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, but that <hi rend="blackletterType">every</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſon had the anointing <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo</hi> in them, as that not any of them needed to be taught, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith not: the anointing Spirit abode in them (in the Body, the Church) ſo as that there was (it ſeems) ſeveral able (through the anointing) to teach and inſtruct the reſt, which is the Will and Mind of the Lord, even for ſpiritual men ſo to do, <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11.</p>
               <p>Object. 'Tis ſaid, That <hi>ye ſhall not teach every man his Brother, ſaying, know the Lord, for all ſhall know me from the leaſt to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,</hi> Heb. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 'Tis to be obſerved, that thoſe whom the Lord ſayes, <hi>ſhall not teach every man his Neighbour,</hi> are ſuch onely as have their ſins forgiven them, (by Faith in Chriſt) and not all men in the world what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever (which is the fence of theſe men) I ſay, onely ſuch, becauſe in that very place 'tis ſaid as from the Lord, even, <hi>that all ſhall know me from the leaſt to the greateſt; for I will be merciful to their unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and their ſins and iniquities will I remember no more,</hi> Heb. 8.12. And this pardon I am ſure (and I think none oppoſes) reaches not every particular man in the world: Therefore all thoſe that have ſo repented of their ſins, believed and obeyed the Lord Jeſus, as to know this gracious pardon reaching them, they indeed <hi>need not teach one another, ſaying, know the Lord,</hi> (as the Children of the old Covenant had need to do, they being Children thereof by generation.) Theſe, I ſay, that are Children of the new Covenant by regeneration, have no need <hi rend="blackletterType">ſo</hi> to teach one another, ſaying, know the Lord, as if they knew not the Lord to be their Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour; for 'tis moſt certain, that he is the Lord and Saviour of all ſuch whoſe <hi>ſins and iniquities he remembreth no more;</hi> but though theſe have no need to ſay to one another, know the Lord, upon the account aforeſaid; yet even theſe have need to be builded up in the knowledge of the Lord, and that by outward means; for <hi>Timothy</hi> knew the Lord as his Saviour, and ſo needed not to be taught to know the Lord, in that ſence; yet <hi>Paul</hi> ſends Scripture unto him, <hi>That he</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">might know how to behave himſelf in the Church of God,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.14,15. And <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith to them that knew the Lord, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Grow in Grace, and in the knowledge of the Lord,</hi> Chap. 3.18. Therefore you that ſerve the Lord in ſimplicity of heart, and fear to offend him, receive the Word of Exhortation, even, <hi>That you ſtand fast, and hold the Traditions which you have been taught, whether</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">by Word or our Epiſtle;</hi> (heed it well, 2 Theſ. 2.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:172158:28"/> 15.) And as for ſuch who will not hear <hi rend="blackletterType">Moſes and the Prophets,</hi> you may be ſure will not be perſwaded, <hi>though one roſe from the dead,</hi> Luke 16.31.</p>
               <p>But withal, let each Soul take good heed, that while they be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to avoid this extream concerning the Light within, the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſence, they do not run out into another extream, alſo dangerous, even, little to mind, or wholly to neglect walking up to the Light they have received within their Souls, according to the Scripture ſence, or Goſpel way of enlightning men; for alas! 'tis not enough for men to know and talk of what is good, what are ſpiritual things; but to do good, and to be ſpiritual: Oh how much more excellent is that! there is the peace known, that others onely hear of, even, the Peace of God <hi>which paſſeth underſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Above all things take the ſhield of Faith, whereby ye ſhall be able to quench all the fiery darts of Satan, and</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">to open the Windows (in your ſervice to God) as afore-time,</hi> Dan. 6.10. <hi>For ſhould</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">ſuch a man as I flee? I will not go in,</hi> ſaith <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> Chap. 6.10,11,13.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>MATTHEW CAFFYN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
